<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jacob wrestling with God, and prevailing: or, a treatise concerning the necessity and efficacy of faith in prayer Wherein divers weighty questions and cases of conscience about praying in faith, are stated and resolved. For the comforting and satisfying of weak and scrupulous consciences: the conviction of formal hypocrites, and awakening of all saints, both weak and strong, great and small, to this great duty of prayer. By one who hath obtained mercy to be a minister of, and sufferer for, the gospel of Jesus Christ in this hour of temptation.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Thomas, 1624 or 5-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833667</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2219:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jacob wrestling with God, and prevailing: or, a treatise concerning the necessity and efficacy of faith in prayer Wherein divers weighty questions and cases of conscience about praying in faith, are stated and resolved. For the comforting and satisfying of weak and scrupulous consciences: the conviction of formal hypocrites, and awakening of all saints, both weak and strong, great and small, to this great duty of prayer. By one who hath obtained mercy to be a minister of, and sufferer for, the gospel of Jesus Christ in this hour of temptation.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Thomas, 1624 or 5-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 196, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>One who hath obtained mercy to be a minister ... = Thomas Taylor.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JACOB Wreſtling with GOD, AND PREVAILING: OR, A Treatiſe concerning the <hi>Neceſsity and Efficacy of Faith</hi> IN PRAYER. Wherein divers weighty Queſtions and Caſes of Conſcience about Praying in Faith, are ſtated and reſolved. For the comforting and ſatisfying of weak and ſcrupulous Conſciences: The Conviction of formal Hypocrites, and awakening of all Saints both weak and ſtrong, great and ſmall, to this great duty of Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By one who hath obtained mercy to be a Miniſter of, and Sufferer for, the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt in this hour of temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 16.24.</hi>
               </bibl> Ask and yee ſhall receive, that your joy may bee full.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoever thou art that takeſt this Book into thy hand, know, that as to thy ſpiritual ſtate, thou art either a Sinner, or a Saint; a Beleever,
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.36 1 Joh. 5.12</note> or an Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, in Chriſt, or out of Chriſt; for betwixt theſe there is no <hi>Medium,</hi> or middle ſtate.</p>
            <p>Now if thou beeſt a ſinner, an unbeleeving Chriſtleſs ſoul,</p>
            <p>Then here is the root of all thy ſpiritual miſery (which is great beyond expreſſion) and the bar, that keeps out all ſpiritual good and mercy from thy ſoul, that thou art at a diſtance, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from communion, the
<pb facs="tcp:38145:3"/>ſweet, and ſoul-enriching, ſoul-ſanctifying, ſoul-ſaving, and ſoul-ſatisfying communion of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Joh. 17.3</note> which is the life of grace, the life of glory, the life of God! <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Alienated form the life of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is thy Hell upon Earth,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.12</note> though thou knoweſt it not; that thou art without God, and without Chriſt in the world, <hi>i. e.</hi> without true ſpiritual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and Jeſus Chriſt, through want of the life and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Faith in thy ſoul, and through a ſinful neglect, or a miſ-performance, as of all other holy duties, ſo eſpecially of this great duty of prayer; in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and right performance whereof, ſuch ſweet and bleſſed communion with God may bee enjoyed; as <hi>Galeatius Caracciolus,</hi> that famous <hi>Italian</hi> Convert (having taſted the ſweetneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:38145:3"/>thereof in his own ſoul, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forſaken all that was dear to him in the world upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) was wont to ſay; <hi>That hee was not worthy the name of a Chriſtian, that did not prize one moments communion with God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a thouſand worlds!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Reader, know, that if thou beeſt ſuch a one as art yet a ſtranger to communion with God; it is one deſign of this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Treatiſe, to lead thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father, by the Son, and to inſtruct thee into this great duty and myſtery of praying in Faith, which if the Lord ſhall give thee rightly to underſtand, and wiſely to improve, will open ſuch a door for eſcape out of thy ſpiritual mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and for the letting in of all ſpiritual mercies and bleſſings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſoul, as may make thee happy to all eternity.</p>
            <p>If thou beeſt a Saint, a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb facs="tcp:38145:4"/>a Soul in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 37.25 Cant. 1.2 Pſal. 63.1, 2, 3.5</note> then to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy communion with him is thy life, thy glory, thy joy, thy crown, thy heaven upon earth; nothing ſo ſweet, nothing ſo precious, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo deſirable to thy ſoul, as communion and fellowſhip with the Father and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, through the ſpirit, and in the conſtant and right uſe and performance of theſe heavenly ordinances, and holy duties, which are the ſweet walks of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.13</note> wherein hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to communicate himſelf to the ſouls of his people; And thoſe ſpiritual Galleries,
<note place="margin">Cant. 7.5</note> in which the King is held and retained by his beloved Spouſe,
<note place="margin">Cant. 4.9</note> in moſt ſweet embraces,
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.4, 5, 6</note> and ſoul-endearing converſes, to the raviſhing of the hearts of each other.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which ſpiritual walks and galleries, there is none in which Jeſus Chriſt doth more
<pb facs="tcp:38145:4"/>delight, and abundantly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate himſelf to the ſouls of his people, than in this great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of prayer, which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called his delight.
<note place="margin">Prov. 15.8</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now 'tis alſo the deſign and ſcope of this Treatiſe, to further thy ſouls communion with Jeſus Chriſt in this ordinance of prayer, by ſhewing thee</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Neceſſity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Efficacy of Faith in Prayer.</p>
            <p>Reſolving divers ſcruples, and Caſes of Conſcience about it.</p>
            <p>Awakening and ſtirring up thy ſoul to it, teaching thee to bee ſpiritual and heavenly in it, and revealing unto thee the great and glorious things that may be done and obtained by it.</p>
            <p>Therefore whether thou beeſt Sinner or Saint, in Chriſt, or out of Chriſt, ſtrong or weak in grace, read this ſmall Treatiſe;
<pb facs="tcp:38145:5"/>and the Lord give thee to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what thou readeſt; ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to imbrace, and faithfully to practice what thou underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and to reap the ſpiritual fruit thereof in grace here, and glory hereafter: And if thou reapeſt any fruit and benefit to thy ſoul by this diſcourſe, give him the glory, who is the Author of Truth, not the Inſtrument. And if thou reapeſt no fruit, or beeſt made worſe by it, blame neither the Author, nor the Inſtrument, but thine own heart as the cauſe of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader. By a Friend of the Authors.</head>
            <p>THis enſuing treatiſe was put into my hand, by the worthy Author ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whoſe humility was jealous of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of this peece; By a curſory view of it, I quickly perceived the ſpirit of it, and preſt to the publiſhing of it, for the relief, quickening, and conſolation of ſuch as underſtand praying in the Holy Ghoſt. And do therefore think meet to acquaint you that the Author of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of prayer, is well known to be a judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and faithful Miniſter of God, and ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, who hath witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a good confeſſion, and that in bonds, for the Commandments of God, and the teſtimony of Jeſus; In which condition, no doubt, his ſoul was converſant in this heavenly exerciſe, and was taken, (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his fellow ſervants,) into a more intimate communion with Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe breathings and cryes, with others of his brethren, are gone up into the ears of the Lord of Hoſts, <hi>Pſa. 97.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:6"/>
            <p>The Accuſer of the Brethren hath great wrath againſt the Spirit of prayer, in this Houre, and hath blaſphemed it at the higheſt rate that ever was heard of in any generation, being greatly tormented thereat, crying out, Oh, Away with this praying in the ſpirit. Wonderful it is, that men pretending Chriſtianity, and to have read the Holy Scriptures, ſhould decry praying in the Spirit, (which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly oppoſed to ſtinted forms) but that the way of the Spirit in the hearts of the called of God, is fooliſhneſs, even to the wiſe and learned that know it not.</p>
            <p>The Author of this Book, as a good witneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, hath given out a holy and experimental Teſtimony to this <hi>Spirit of prayer,</hi> and hath diſcovered the <hi>abomination</hi> of Hypocritical pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the <hi>vain repetitions</hi> and <hi>ſaying long prayers for a pretence,</hi> Mat. <hi>6.7.</hi> and <hi>23.14.</hi> to juſtle out the ſpirit of prayer, promiſed to <hi>all Miniſters</hi> ſent by Jeſus Chriſt, and <hi>all Saints,</hi> eſpecially in the New Teſtament daies. If this therfore come into the hands of any pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſs ſouls, know thou art yet <hi>without the ſpirit,</hi> and ſo art <hi>none of Jeſus
<pb facs="tcp:38145:6"/>Chriſts.</hi> Rom. <hi>8.9.</hi> Where-ever the <hi>Spirit of Grace</hi> is, it is a <hi>Spirit of prayer,</hi> Zach. <hi>12.10.</hi> Doſt thou feel the guilt of ſin, the want of pardon, peace, grace, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, thou wouldſt not need the words of others to help thee in praying, but thou wouldſt know what it is, for the <hi>ſpirit to help</hi> (the proper and onely help in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) thy <hi>infirmities,</hi> and couldſt bee no more ſatisfied with dry and empty forms, then a hungry man with Air.</p>
            <p>If thou art a weak doubting ſoul, and complaineſt of an unbelieving heart, (which is a good ſymptome) here thou mayeſt meet with plain and ſpiritual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to thy doubts, about the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thy prayer, and the looking for anſwers thereof, and what faith thou art to exerciſe on promiſes in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>Yea all Saints may be further inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the efficacy and prevalency of prayer, and to be encouraged that the Lord will not caſt off a praying Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that cry day and night unto him. The Lord hasten to power forth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of light and prayer upon his people and upon the world, as the beſt ſign of his own approaching to judge the earth. In
<pb facs="tcp:38145:7"/>the waiting for which, let all that have received the firſt fruits thereof be found at this day; To which expectation, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, I commend thee, and this ſpiritual treatiſe to thy peruſal, and it, and thy ſelf to the bleſſing made over to the ſeed of Jacob, that wraſtle it out with God, and prevail over him. The Saints do in a ſenſe, govern the World with Jeſus, Chriſt already, by the ſpirit of Prayer that is in them, making interceſſion in them according to Christs interceſſion in heaven, and uſually wee may know what God is about to do in the world by the prayers of his Saints, eſpecially in this laſt age of the world, when their ſouls travel and are in pangs for Sions Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and the earth-quake to come into the Nations of the world, till all the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of it, (as laid for the intereſt of <hi>Babylon</hi> and Antichriſtianiſm) are ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and out of courſe, which the Lord will <hi>haſten in his time.</hi> But I muſt break off, and be-ſpeak thy prayers for the Author and my ſelf, and all the Lords afflicted Miniſters, that are mourning in corners, reſting,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant for Jeſus ſake.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38145:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtling with God, and prevailing.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 21.22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And all things whatſoever ye ſhall ask in Prayer beleeving, ye ſhall receive.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text is brought in as an <hi>Epiphonema</hi> or Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpeech to the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the fruitleſs Fig-tree, which being curſed by Jeſus Chriſt for its barrenneſs, preſently withers, and is dried up, <hi>v.</hi> 19. to the great admiration of the Diſciples, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. which action, as it was extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and miraculous in its ſelf, ſo in the tendency thereof it was of extraordinary uſe to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38145:8"/>Diſciples, and did carry along with it a double inſtruction.</p>
               <p>Firſt, To beware of an outſide formal Profeſſion, without ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual fruit, and a ſuitable conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which is alway attended with the wrath and diſpleaſure of God, and is nigh unto curſing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To teach the great Efficacy and Power of Faith, and what great things may be done thereby, either extraordinary, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that diſpenſation of working miracles, which was but for the time preſent, and peculiar to ſome, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. for all had not this gift, nor faith of miracles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29.30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or elſe ordinary, according to the gift and force of prayer, which is perpetual and common to all the Saints, by which they have a conſtant and joynt acceſs to the Throne of Grace in all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38145:8"/>cauſes whatſoever, and may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly prevail with God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they pray in Faith as in the Text. <hi>And all things whatſoever, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Text of Scripture there are two things principally taught and commended to our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Neceſſity of Faith in Prayer.</item>
                  <item>2. The Efficacy of Faith in Prayer.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The Neceſſity of Faith in Prayer, is gathered from the word <hi>[Beleeving]</hi> which is brought in as a ſpecifical and qualifying adjunct, or neceſſary ingredient to all our prayers. <hi>And all things whatſoever ye ſhall ask in prayer</hi> beleeving, <hi>ye ſhall receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Neceſſity of Faith in Prayer, is alſo gathered from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Texts of Scripture, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>But without Faith it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe God; for he that cometh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38145:9"/>to God muſt beleeve, &amp;c.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>James</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>If any of you lack wiſdome, let him ask of God, &amp;c. But let him ask in Faith.</hi> And look, as the body without the ſoul is dead and uſeleſs, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perform the actions of a man: So alſo Prayer without Faith, is dead and unprofitable, <hi>James</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. So that Faith is the ſoul and life of Prayer, and therefore a neceſſary ingredient thereto.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Queſt. or Caſe of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what kinde of Faith is that which is ſo neceſſarily and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly required in all our prayers to God? is it the Faith of Aſſurance? or the Faith of Relyance? ſeeing</hi> James <hi>ſaith,</hi> it muſt be without wavering, and in nothing doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Therefore it would ſeem that there is required in all our prayers to God, a Faith of Aſſurance, yea, of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38145:9"/>full and perfect Aſſurance, which admits of no doubting or uncertainty of the mind in the thing asked, and that a Faith of Relyance is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, ſeeing that is alwaies attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome doubting, as in</hi> Eſther, [If I periſh, I periſh] <hi>ſhe relyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God in the uſe of means, but yet was doubtful as to the ſucceſs and event thereof. Now if this Faith be not accepted in prayer, then the prayers of moſt of the Children of God are ineffectual, ſeeing moſt of them have not the Faith of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſaying of the holy man <hi>James,</hi> ſhall be cleared in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But in anſwer to the Queſtion, it is affirmed, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be the duty of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to preſs after the Faith of Aſſurance, as that which tendeth exceedingly to their comfort and inward joy: Yet where there is a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38145:10"/>Faith of Relyance, <hi>i.e.</hi> the heart doth inwardly reſt upon Gods al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency, mercy, faithfulneſs, truth, &amp;c. yet with doubting and uncertainty of the mind, whether the thing ſhall be done which is asked of God in prayer; the prayer is accepted of God, and ſhall certainly have a gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in due time.</p>
               <p>But that we may be the more clear and diſtinct in our handling this point, to the ſatisfaction and comfort of weak and ſcrupulous conſciences: we ſhall firſt give a brief deſcription of theſe two kinds of Faith, in their diſtinct and different natures; that ſo the perſon who is ſcrupulous may the better judge of his Faith, of what kinde it is: And then wee ſhall by Scripture and experience make good our aſſertion, <hi>viz.</hi> that a Faith of Relyance is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God in prayer, where
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38145:10"/>the faith of Aſſurance is wanting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith of Aſſurance deſcribed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Faith of Aſſurance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a full perſwaſion,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22 1 Joh. 5.13, 14, 15 1 Joh. 5.6 Rom. 8.16</note> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Aſſurance of the mind of a Beleever, of the thing asked or hoped for, grounded upon the clear and infallible teſtimony of the Word and Spirit of God in their joynt witneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith of Relyance deſcribed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Faith of Relyance is the inward reſting of the heart upon God, his name and attributes,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 37.7 Jonah 3.8, 9 Eſther 4.16 Job 13.15 Dan. 3.17, 18</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> his power, wiſdome, mercy, faithfulneſs, truth, &amp;c. for the performance of his Word and Promiſe in general, without any certainty or aſſurance of the mind, with application thereof to its ſelf in ſpecial, wanting the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular witneſs and teſtimony of the Spirit in the caſe, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38145:11"/>is preſent in the Faith of Aſſurance, but alwaies abſent and wanting in this Faith of Rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Of this kind was the Faith of the Leper, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.2. <hi>[Lord if thou wilt thou canſt make me clean]</hi> there was a relyance upon the power of Chriſt to do the thing asked, but a doubtfulneſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the mind as touching the application of that ability and healing power to himſelf in particular. And therefore he puts it with an if; <hi>[Lord if thou wilt]</hi> ſpeaking of his particular and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret will in the caſe propounded, which was not yet made known, and therefore he might without ſin doubt of it: But as to his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral will, and infinite readineſs to heal the ſick, cleanſe the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, &amp;c. which was abundantly revealed and made known both by Scripture and Experience, he could not have doubted thereof,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38145:11"/>without great ſin; and ſo would conſequently have been reproved for it.</p>
               <p>Thus having deſcribed theſe two kinds of Faith, in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and different natures, whereby every one that cometh unto God by prayer, may be able to judge of himſelf, and know what kinde of Faith it is, that he comes withall. We ſhall proceed to make good the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Aſſer.</hi> That a Faith of Rely ance is accepted with God in prayer, where a Faith of Aſſurance is wanting. <hi>Proved,</hi>
               </q>
               <p n="1">1. By Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. <hi>It is accepted according to what a man hath, and not according to what he hath not.</hi> The general e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and force of which Rule reacheth not onely unto the caſe of Alms; to which the Apoſtle doth there apply it, but alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38145:12"/>all other caſes wherein wee have to do with God, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly unto this caſe of prayer, for otherwiſe God ſhould ſeem to be a hard Maſter, reaping where he hath not ſown, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering where he hath not ſtrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and expecting to receive, where hee hath not firſt given, which cannot at any time, nor in any caſe be juſtly ſaid of him, who is infinite in mercy, and with whom there is no unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all whoſe commands are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual and reaſonable. And who receiveth not from his creature, but according to the gift of his own grace, which hee hath firſt beſtowed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.35. <hi>[or who hath firſt given to him?]</hi> Now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Faith is not of our ſelves, but is in an eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the gift of God, who work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things after the counſel of his own will, and planteth in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38145:12"/>hearts of his people different kinds and meaſures of grace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the uſe he intends to make of them: It remains, that where the Lord hath wrought a Faith of Relyance in the hearts of his people, to whom he hath not given the Faith of Aſſurance. And they come to him in prayer, and in the uſe of all holy means which he hath appointed for the good of their ſouls, with ſuch a Faith as himſelf hath wrought in them; he doth graciouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them according to what they have, and not according to what they have not.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> 2. By Experience; and this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is manifeſt by the common and conſtant experience of the Saints, who when they have ſo come to God in prayer, with a Faith of Adherence, where Aſſurance have been wanting, have been
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38145:13"/>graciouſly accepted of the Lord and received a gracious anſwer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch Prayers. As in the caſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Leper above-mentioned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.2, 3. who when he came to Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in prayer, only in a Faith of Rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon his power to help when as he had no aſſurance of his particular will and purpoſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to himſelf, and therefore puts a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if upon that; <hi>[Lord if thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou canſt make mee clean]</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> graciouſly accepted of the Lord, and obtained a ſpeedy and full anſwer of that prayer, in the very thing he asked, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>[And Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus put forth his hand, and touched him, ſaying, (I will) be thou clean, and immediately his Leproſie was cleanſed.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> And ſo likewiſe in the caſe of the Woman of <hi>Canaan, Mat.</hi> 15.22, — 29. who came to Chriſt in prayer on the behalf of her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted daughter, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Saying,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38145:13"/>Have mercy on mee, O Lord, thou Son of David, my daughter is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly vexed with a Devil.</hi> Now here was wrought in this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (though a <hi>Canaanite,</hi> a ſtranger, an alien from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) a mighty Faith of Relyance, by which ſhe did marvelouſly cling to Jeſus the Son of <hi>David,</hi> relying upon his mercy, and power, to help her, though ſhee had no certain aſſurance, that ſhee ſhould have her petition granted; but many diſcouraging paſſages from Chriſt. As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, His ſilence to her prayer, anſwering her not a word, <hi>v.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Secondly, His ſeeming denial of her requeſt, with this reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; <hi>That he was not ſent, ſave to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> verſ. 24.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. His upbraiding her with her ſtock and generation; being
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38145:14"/>deſcended of the curſed ſtoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and generation of the <hi>Canaanite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in reſpect whereof he calls her a dog, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. by all which it is moſt clear, ſhe neither had, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could have any aſſurance, but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ly ſhe exerciſeth her Faith of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance, notwithſtanding all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and diſcouragements, and ſtill ſhe prayes, and worſhips th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Son of <hi>David,</hi> confeſſing her own vileneſs and unworthineſs, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Juſtifying the Lord in calling he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dog, and taking advantage there upon to hope that yet there might beſome crumbs of mercy for her <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Truth Lord, yet the Dog eat the crumbs that fall from their Maſters table.</hi> And at length with this Faith ſhe prevails, and hath a full anſwer of her petition, with a high commendation of her Faith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Then Jeſus an ſwered and ſaid unto her, O Woman great is thy Faith! be it unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38145:14"/>even as thou wilt: And her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was made whole the ſame hour.</hi> And ſo much by way of anſwer to the firſt Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Queſt. or Caſe of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But whether is it ſufficient to have the habit and being of Faith in the heart when we pray? or is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and acting of Faith neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it is not ſufficient to have the habit and being of Faith in the heart when we pray, but the exerciſe and actuality of our Faith is required in our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God by prayer: 'tis not enough that the perſon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be a Beleever, but alſo that the prayer made be a prayer of Faith, or a beleeving Prayer: hence it is put in the preſent tenſe: <hi>[Beleeving] And all things whatſoever ye ſhall ask in prayer [be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving]</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38145:15"/>not having beleeved, but beleeving, in the preſent tenſe: intimating to us, that a preſent exerciſe of Faith is required; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the prayer may be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving, and ſo by conſequence a fruitleſs prayer, though the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be a beleever; for a godly man may make a carnal prayer; a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving man may make an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving prayer. As the good man <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſeems to do, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7, 7, 8, 9. The truth is, wee are ſaid to have no more Faith than we act. And therefore Jeſus Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves his Diſciples as faithleſs, when, as 'tis clear, they wanted not the habit, but the exerciſe of Faith in that particular caſe of caſting out the dumb ſpirit, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.19. Thoſe prayers therefore are faithleſs prayers, in which there is not a preſent exerciſe of faith, though the perſon or perſons praying, be in a ſtate of grace,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38145:15"/>and have the habit of Faith in their hearts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Queſt or Caſe of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the exerciſe and actuality of Faith be neceſſarily required in all things whatſoever we ask of God in the name of Chriſt, then whether may ſuch an exerciſe of Faith be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as is accompanied with ſome doubting and wavering of the mind? or is ſuch an exerciſe of Faith only current with God in Prayer, as is clear and ſtedfaſt, without the leaſt doubt or wavering?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon of this ſcruple or queſtion is, that ſaying of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man <hi>James,</hi> in his <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>But let him ask in Faith, nothing wavering; for he that wavereth is like a wave of the Sea, driven with the wind, and toſſed; for let not that man think, that he ſhall receive any thing of the Lord.</hi> Now if ſuch an exerciſe of Faith, as is attended
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38145:16"/>with ſome doubting, be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God, and the prayers of ſuch be altogether fruitleſs and unprofitable, as this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeemeth to import, then is the hope, comfort and experience of the moſt of Gods Children thereby cut off and denyed; And if otherwiſe, then how is this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>James</hi> to bee underſtood, and reconciled with other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Two kinds of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> There is a twofold doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or wavering of the mind, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in Scripture.</p>
               <p>The one which doth alwaies exclude and oppoſe Faith; ſo that where ſuch doubting is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is not the leaſt acting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtirring of Faith in the heart.</p>
               <p>The other, which doth onely argue weakneſs of Faith, and is conſiſtent with the exerciſe and actuality thereof at the ſame time in ſome degree.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:38145:16"/>
               <p>The ſaying of the holy man <hi>James</hi> above-mentioned, is to be underſtood onely of the former,
<note n="1" place="margin">Kind ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch doubting or wavering of the mind, as doth oppoſe Faith, and is excluſive to it; as is clear by the antitheſis or oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith, and wavering being ſet in the Text the one againſt the other; for ſaith <hi>James, Let him ask in Faith;</hi> And then hee oppoſes thereunto this word <hi>[wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering] nothing wavering,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> not diſputing or cavilling; ſo that 'tis manifeſt the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of ſuch a doubting or wavering, as argues a nullity and privation of Faith, where there is no beleeving of the Promiſe and Word of God, but a diſputing and cavilling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and an oppoſing of it. As in the caſe of that Lord, on whoſe hand the King leaned, when the Prophet by the Word
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38145:17"/>of the Lord fore-told ſo great plenty to be on the morrow in the gate of <hi>Samaria;</hi> who diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and reaſoning againſt the Promiſe and Word of God, out of an unbeleeving heart, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the man of God: <hi>Behold, if the Lord would make windows in Heaven, might this thing bee?</hi> 2 King. 7.1, 2. This was ſuch a wavering as <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, which argued a nullity of Faith, and ſtrength of unbeleef in the heart of that Noble man, who thus diſputed and cavilled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Promiſe, giving no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the Word of the Lord, ſpoken by the Prophet, nor in the leaſt acknowledging or rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the power of God, for the performance thereof: And therefore was made a ſpectacle of divine vengeance, for his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and unbeleef, being trodden to death the next day in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38145:17"/>the gate, which verified the Word ſpoken to him by the Prophet: <hi>Thou ſhalt ſee it with thine eyes, but ſhalt not eat thereof,</hi> verſ. 2. compared with <hi>v.</hi> 19, 20.</p>
               <p>And of ſuch a doubting as this is that ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to be underſtood, <hi>Rom</hi> 14.23. <hi>And he that doubteth is damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe he eateth not of Faith; for whatſoever is not of Faith, is ſin.</hi> 'Tis evident in this place the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh of ſuch a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as argues a want of Faith, and right underſtanding of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, in that particular action of eating: In which hee that eateth without Faith, is condemned in his own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though the thing in it ſelf be lawful, yet to him it is ſinful and unlawful, for want of Faith in what he doth: Otherwiſe a man is not condemned in that action which he doth with ſome
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38145:18"/>doubting; wherein there is alſo a real and true exerciſe of Faith, though in a weak and low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. As <hi>Simon</hi> in letting down the Net at the command of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.5.</p>
               <p>The ſecond kind of doubting or wavering ſpoken of in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note n="2" place="margin">Kind ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note> is ſuch a doubting as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the preſent exerciſe of Faith, and argues only weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Faith, but not the want of it; which kind of doubting is found in the true Children of God, even in their beſt duties oft times; the conſideration whereof doth alſo much trouble and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them. Now this kind of doubting,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.13 Mat. 8.26 Mat. 14.31</note> though it is ſinful, and to be reproved, yet being a ſin of infirmity, and weakneſs, not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wilful rebellion, or preſumption, the Lord doth in mercy cover and paſs it by in his people, and doth not therefore reject their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38145:18"/>perſons, or any their ſincere and faithful ſervices, but doth gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly accept them in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, notwithſtanding ſuch infirmities as by the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtances doth appear.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> And thus <hi>Sarah</hi> was accepted of God in the exerciſe of her weak Faith, when the Lord made a promiſe of a Son to be given her in her old age, though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe was not without ſome doubting, as appeareth by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.12, 13, 14. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.11. In the former, <hi>viz. Gen.</hi> 18.13. She is reproved for her doubting: <hi>Wherefore did Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah laugh? is any thing too hard for the Lord?</hi> But in the latter, <hi>viz.</hi> Heb. 11.11. She is commended and approved for her Faith at the ſame time, and in the ſame action; <hi>Through Faith alſo Sarah her ſelf received ſtrength to conceive ſeed, and was delivered of a childe when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38145:19"/>ſhe was paſt age, becauſe ſhe judged him faithful who had promiſed:</hi> So that by comparing theſe two Scriptures, which relate to the ſame perſon and action, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that <hi>Sarahs</hi> doubting through weakneſs of Faith, did not hinder her acceptance with God in that action, wherein there was the real exerciſe of her Faith, though weak and wavering: for ſaith the Text, <hi>Shee judged him faithful who had promiſed;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe did believe the promiſe, and relye upon the faithfulneſs of God for the performance thereof, notwithſtanding the great doubting and ſtirring of unbeleef in her heart at the ſame time, which yet ſhe reſiſted, and alſo at length did overcome. Whence theſe two things may truly be gathered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That great doubting and wavering of the mind may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38145:19"/>with the real, though weak exerciſe of Faith in the ſame ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly action.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſuch holy actions are accepted of God in Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſuch doubtings.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> The truth of this doth alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the caſe of him who brought his childe to Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſſed with a dumb ſpirit. And now finding his caſe to be exceeding difficult, in that he had already tryed the Diſciples; and they could not caſt out this dumb ſpirit out of his Son, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.18. hee begins through unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leef to haeſitate and doubt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the power of Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and puts an [if] upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>But [if] thou canſt do any thing, have compaſsion on us and help us:</hi> ſo that here was great doubting and ſtirring of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleef, which Chriſt reproves, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. and replyes to him; <hi>If
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38145:20"/>thou canſt beleeve, all things are poſsible to him that beleeveth;</hi> which reproof of Chriſt prevails ſo far upon him to the breaking of his heart, and humbling of him for his unbeleef, that hee cryes out with tears, from a ſenſe of his ſin, as well as of his childes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, <hi>Lord, I beleeve, help mine unbeleef.</hi> Now here was ſome Faith mixed with great doubting and unbeleef, yet being bewaile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and confeſſed, the prayer of this diſtreſſed and afflicted Father, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the behalf of his childe, is heard and anſwered; for the dumb ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is caſt out, and his child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> healed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25, 26, 27.</p>
               <p>Oh the infinite riches, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> condeſcention of free grace! tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ever ſuch a prayer as this ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be heard and anſwered, that pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an [if] upon the power of Chriſt <hi>[If thou canſt do any thing, have compaſsion on us]</hi> And yet there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38145:20"/>being found ſome Faith in this prayer (though attended with ſo great doubting and acting of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleef) it is accepted and owned by the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>The anſwer and reſolution therefore of the queſtion, is, That although it be the duty of the people of God, to preſs after ſuch Faith in prayer, as is without doubting and wavering of the mind: And all ſuch doubting and wavering of the mind, is in it ſelf ſinful, and to be reproved; and by no means to be cheriſhed and allowed: Yet ſuch doubting and wavering as doth ariſe onely from weakneſs of Faith in the minde of a beleever (where there is alſo a real exerciſe of Faith, though in the weakeſt and loweſt degree) doth not, nor can at any time hinder the acceptance and efficacy of their prayers with God;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.6 1 Pet. 2.5 James 5.17, 18</note> but their perſons and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38145:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:38145:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:38145:22"/>prayers are acceptable to God, through Chriſt Jeſus, with a <hi>Notwithſtanding</hi> to all ſuch infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Queſt. or Caſe of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the exerciſe of Faith be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily required in all our prayers to God, then whether is it at all times, and in all caſes required, that hee who cometh to God in prayer, doth abſolutely and determinately believe for the very thing, that he prayeth for? or that hee prayeth with a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion to the will of God, either to have the thing that he prayeth for; or that which the Lord may ſee to be better for him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The occaſion and ground of this Queſtion, is, That ſome Chriſtians being earneſtly carried out in prayer againſt ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular luſt or corruption, as pride, envy, inordinate love to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or againſt the inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38145:22"/>and luſtings of any other ſin, which they feel ſtirring in themſelves, praying that the ſame may be removed, and taken out of the way, or for any other particular mercy which they have an earneſt deſire to obtain at the hands of God: Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they finde not an anſwer in the very thing asked, but the ſame luſt or corruption remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſtill unſubdued, and the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſo greatly deſired, ſtill denied, notwithſtanding all their prayers; They uſually conclude, that they prayed not in Faith, and that their prayers are not at all accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or anſwered, becauſe they have not the thing asked; refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their caſe to that of <hi>James</hi> 4.3. <hi>Yee ask, and receive not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yee ask amiſs.</hi> And not only in this caſe of inbred corruption, but alſo in many other caſes Chriſtians are much put to it, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38145:23"/>know when they ask in Faith, and when they ask amiſs: Many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding they ask not in Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not the very thing asked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The exerciſe of our Faith in prayer, muſt be either abſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and determinate in the very thing asked, or conditional and latitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, referring to what may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt agreeable to the will o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, whether it be the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing asked, or ſomething elſe according to the nature of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing which we ask.</p>
               <p>The Rule therefore which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtle propoſeth to himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> concerning prayer, is diligent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to be obſerved by every Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>I will pray wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Spirit; and I will pray with u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding alſo.</hi> It therefore co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every Chriſtian to unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of the thing which hee asks of God in praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:38145:23"/>otherwiſe hee may ask amiſs.</p>
               <p>The things which we ask of God in prayer, may fall under a double diſtinction.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of our ſelves; which every Chriſtian ought diligently to mark and conſider, that ſo hee may frame his peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and exerciſe his Faith therein, according to the Rule of the Word; for Faith is guided by the light of the Word, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go againſt the Word, nor without the Word in any thing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of God.</p>
               <p>The things which we come to ask of him in prayer, are either clearly and abſolutely revealed, promiſed, and fore-told in his Word; or elſe ſecret, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, which hee hath reſerved in his own power.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of our ſelves. The things which we come to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38145:24"/>ask of God in prayer, are either abſolutely, and <hi>perſe</hi> good and neceſſary for us; or they are good and neceſſary for us onely upon ſuch and ſuch variable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, and ſuppoſitions, as wee are very apt to miſtake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
               <p>Now to apply theſe general Rules to our caſe and queſtion in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>1</label> In things which are clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, abſolutely fore-told and promiſed in the Word of God, we ought to act our Faith abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and determinately for the very thing we pray for, and not to admit the leaſt doubt or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but to maintain an holy confidence, that ſuch prayers are alwaies heard, though not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently anſwered; as 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.14, 15. <hi>And this is the confidence that wee have in him, that if wee ask any thing according to his will,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38145:24"/>he heareth us. And if wee know that hee heareth us, whatſoever we ask, wee know that wee have the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions that wee deſired of him.</hi> There is no room for the leaſt doubt or ſcruple in ſuch things which wee ask according to his will; but wee are to pray with full aſſurance of Faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ſuch caſes, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing wee ask is granted. As for inſtance in ſome particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> Suppoſe I pray for the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall and utter ruine of <hi>Babylon</hi> (that <hi>Mother of Harlots.</hi>) I am to beleeve in prayer abſolutely and determinately (without If or And) that the very thing which I now ask, is granted in Heaven, and ſhall be performed in due time; becauſe God hath clearly revealed, and abſolutely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told and promiſed the ſame in his Word, for the comfort of his Church and People, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.2.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:38145:25"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> If I ask of God in prayer, the deliverance of his Church and People out of the hands of their wicked enemies, that do afflict them; I ought to pray in full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Faith, and with ſure confidence, that the very thing which I ask, is done in Heaven, and ſhall be certainly accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Gods due time, becauſe he hath clearly revealed, fore-told, and promiſed the ſame in his moſt holy Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.39.40.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>3</label> So likewiſe, when I ask of God in prayer, the ſpiritual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and keeping of his Elect in a time of tryal and temptation, that not one of them may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, nor the gates of Hell pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt them, to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their Faith. Herein I am poſitively to beleeve, that I have the very thing which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of God, becauſe hee hath clearly revealed, and abſolutely
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38145:25"/>promiſed the ſame in his Word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. And ſo in all other petitions for things of this nature.</p>
               <p>In things which are not clearly revealed,
<note place="margin">Second part of the Rule</note> nor abſolutely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Word of God, but left dubious, obſcure, and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as to us, the mind of the Lord concerning the ſame not being declared: wee are not in ſuch caſes to beleeve poſitively for the thing that wee ask of God, but to refer our ſelves to his wiſdome and choice therein, with ſubmiſſion to his holy will.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> Thus the <hi>Ninivites</hi> in that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn work of faſting and prayer, joyned with repentance, did not, nor could poſitively beleeve for the thing they asked of God, <hi>viz.</hi> the averſion of that national wrath which did hang over their head; but came to God in prayer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38145:26"/>with a [may be of Faith] a [per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure] a who can tell, <hi>if God will turn and repent, and turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his fierce anger, that wee periſh not,</hi> Jonah 3.9. and yet were accepted of God therein, and had their petition granted, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> So <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.3. <hi>The meek of the earth</hi> are there exhorted to ſeek the Lord, to ſeek meekneſs, to ſeek righteouſneſs, with this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: <hi>It may be yee ſhall be his in the day of the Lords anger.</hi> Where the mind and will of the Lord in the caſe is not clearly revealed and made known: There no more is required than a may be of Faith; for Faith cannot go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Word of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>3</label> In this reſpect alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Act. 8.22. <hi>Repent therefore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God; if [per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps] the thought of thine heart
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38145:26"/>may be forgiven thee.</hi> His ſin was great, his caſe very difficult and ſingular; the mind of the Lord not certainly known: Therefore the Apoſtle exhorts him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and to pray; but it muſt be onely with a may be, not a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of obtaining, with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps: <hi>[if perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>2</label> In things which we ask of God in prayer, which are abſolutely and ſimply good and neceſſary for us. Wee are to beleeve and act our Faith poſitively upon the Promiſe and Word of God, for the very thing that wee pray for, without any doubting or waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the caſe. As ſuppoſe I come to God in prayer to ask of him ſuch a meaſure of grace and wiſdome, as may inable and fit mee to diſcharge my duty in my place and ſtation, in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as may be to his glory, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38145:27"/>the good of his people: here my duty is to act Faith upon his Word and Promiſe abſolutely; for the thing I ask, without the leaſt doubting or wavering, for ſo I am commanded, <hi>James</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>If any man lack wiſdome, let him ask of God, &amp;c. But let him ask in Faith, nothing waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> There is no room for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or wavering in ſuch a caſe as this; in things of this nature.</p>
               <p>It is not lawful to doubt or waver, though in ſome other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it may be lawful, as hath been already ſhewed; which hint may give ſome further light to the right underſtanding of this text of Scripture, which reacheth not unto all caſes, but onely unto ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this or the like nature.</p>
               <p>A pregnant inſtance in this caſe,
<note place="margin">Inſtance.</note> is that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 Kings 3.5, 7, 8, 9. Where <hi>Solomon,</hi> from a ſenſe of Gods great goodneſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38145:27"/>in calling him to ſo great a place, and of his own great unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and inability to manage the ſame, to Gods glory, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good. Omitting other things of more private concernment, he makes his requeſt to God for Wiſdome and Underſtanding, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to his place and ſtation, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Give therefore thy ſervant an underſtanding heart, to judge thy people, that I may diſcern between good and bad; For who is able to judge this thy ſo great a people?</hi> It being a thing abſolutely good and neceſſary for him, in order to Gods glory, and his peoples good; he asks abſolutely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminately for this very thing, and no other, in exchange for it, and how acceptable and well pleaſing this requeſt of <hi>Solomon</hi> was in the ſight of the Lord, is ſufficiently declared in the ſtory, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38145:28"/>
               <p>But in things which are not abſolutely and <hi>per ſe</hi> good and neceſſary for us,
<note place="margin">Laſt part of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Rule.</note> but may be good or bad for us upon ſuch variable conſiderations, which are beſt known to God, and about which wee are very apt to miſtake: In all ſuch caſes wee are not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve for the very thing which wee ask, but by Faith to relye upon, and refer our ſelves to the wiſdome of God, for that which hee ſeeth beſt for us.</p>
               <p>Neither are we raſhly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that wee have asked amiſs, and our prayers are not heard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee have not the very thing wee deſire; foraſmuch as in all ſuch caſes there is an exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Faith, in ſubmitting ſuch deſires of ours unto the will of God.</p>
               <p>Either <hi>Expreſſed</hi> or <hi>Underſtood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Expreſſed:</hi> As in that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38145:28"/>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. <hi>O my Father, if it be poſsible let this Cup paſs from mee; nevertheleſs, not as I will, but as thouwilt.</hi> Which exerciſe of his Faith, in ſubmitting to his Fathers will, is yet more vigorous, <hi>v.</hi> 42. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>hee was heard, in that he feared;</hi> for, though hee was not heard in the very thing asked, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Cup might paſs from him; yet he was heard in that, wherein he ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf to his Fathers will.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> 2. <hi>Implicite</hi> or <hi>underſtood,</hi> as in that petition of <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee prayed againſt the thorn in the fleſh, that it might depart from him, 2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 12.8. In which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition queſtionleſs he did exerciſe his Faith, and beleeved, though not poſitively, that hee ſhould have the very thing hee asked; yet that hee ſhould have either that thing, <hi>viz.</hi> the taking away the thorn in his fleſh, or elſe that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38145:29"/>which the Lord at that time ſhould ſee to be better for him, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſufficiency of grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and withſtand it. In which reſpect his petition was granted, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. And hee ſaid unto mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which was much better for him at that time, than that it ſhould have departed from him; for hee ſtood in great need of ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe at that time. And the thor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his fleſh, though it was ſharp and grievous to him, was of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial uſe and benefit to him, to keep him humble, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſpiritual pride, and ſelf-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation after his abundance of Revelations, and high enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>And leaſt I ſhould be exalted above meaſure, through the abundance of Revelations, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was given to mee a thorn in the fleſh; the meſſenger of Satan to buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet mee, leaſt I ſhould be exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:38145:29"/>
               <p>Hence wee may obſerve and learn, that the Lord knoweth how to make uſe of the Saints inbred corruptions, and Satans temptations, for their good and benefit: And therefore when we pray againſt the motions and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of inward corruption, and Satans temptations, that they may be taken from us. It ought to be with this <hi>proviſo</hi> and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion expreſſed or implied, if the Lord ſeeth the ſame to be good for us, otherwiſe to have ſuch a ſufficiency of his grace, as may inable us to reſiſt and withſtand them: for though the preſence of ſuch things be as a thorn in our fleſh, <hi>i. e.</hi> very grievous and troubleſome to us; yet thereby many times a greater evil is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, <hi>viz.</hi> ſpiritual pride, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence, ſelf-conceitedneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though ſuch motions of inbred corruption and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38145:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:38145:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:38145:31"/>of Satan are ſinful: Yet where they are reſiſted and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by Faith, Prayer, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, &amp;c. they are not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17. <hi>Now therefore it is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more I that do it, but ſin that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in mee.</hi> Yea ſuch motions and ſtirrings of the fleſh, and buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetings of Satan, are oft-times given to the children of God in great mercy to prevent a greater evil, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>There was given mee a thorn in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that in ſuch caſes Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may not conclude that their prayers againſt ſuch motions and temptations, are not heard, or that they have not prayed in Faith, becauſe they are not preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and taken away; for there is an exerciſe and work of Faith in ſubmitting ſuch deſires unto the wiſdome and will of God, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38145:31"/>an anſwer is given to ſuch prayers, though not in the very thing deſired, yet in that which the Lord knoweth to be better for them; as in this caſe of <hi>Paul</hi> is moſt clear; hee prayes, and he prayes earneſtly, and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, That the thorn in his fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan, might depart from him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>For this thing I beſought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from mee.</hi> And hee hath his prayer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not in the thing deſired, but in that which was better for him at preſent, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> The thorn in his fleſh, the buffeting of Satan remaineth, notwithſtanding all his prayers againſt it: and yet his prayer is heard and anſwered, in that hee hath a ſufficient mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace and ſtrength from Chriſt to reſiſt and withſtand it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> So likewiſe in that caſe of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38145:32"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the wilderneſs, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being ſtung by the fiery flyin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Serpents, the ſting whereof w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deadly, and by which many dye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they come to <hi>Moſes</hi> with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> requeſt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.7. <hi>Pray un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lord, that hee take away t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Serpents from us.</hi> And <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> prayed for the people: And though hee was not heard in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very thing asked, <hi>viz.</hi> That th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Serpents ſhould be taken away which queſtionleſs they though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be beſt for them; yet was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer anſwered in the lifting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Brazen Serpent; whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon other conſiderations th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord ſaw to be better for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at that time. So <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lord ſaid unto Moſes, Make thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fiery Serpent, and ſet it upon a po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and it ſhall come to paſs, that ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one that is bitten, when hee looke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon it ſhall live.</hi> Wherein wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exhibited a moſt lively type <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38145:32"/>Chriſt, and of that healing vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which the children of God do receive from him by Faith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deadly ſting of ſin. The ſting whereof would bee deadly unto them, as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others, were they not healed by looking unto Jeſus Chriſt, who was lift up for that very end, <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.14, 15. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many the dear children of God, when they feel this ſting in their conſciences, do pray earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and importunately to have theſe Serpents of their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red corruptions, and Satans temptations taken away, that they might never more be ſtung and hurt by them (who though they do well to expreſs their zeal, hatred, and holy indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſin, which queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs is well pleaſing in the ſight of God) yet in praying ſo poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ively and abſolutely to have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38145:33"/>theſe removed, they do not pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with that underſtanding an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowledge they ought, neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do they therein pray according to the will of God, otherwiſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by an implicite ſubmiſſion, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alwaies ought to accompany ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> petitions:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.24.25 1 Joh. 2.1, 2 1 Joh. 1.9</note> But have ſuch prayer anſwered in the remedy vouch ſafed in Chriſt, which is beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all.</p>
               <p>Having as briefly as wee w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could, paſſed through theſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and weighty queſtions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> caſes of conſcience, about the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Faith in prayer, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſatisfaction and comfort of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hidden ones, whoſe property it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not to take things of this natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon truſt, but conſcientiouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> enquire, till they be ſatisfacton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſolved from the Word of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and have proved what his go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and acceptable will, and their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is, in all things pertaining to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:38145:33"/>worſhip and ſervice; and wherein ſo much of their ſpiritual peace and comfort is bound up, we ſhall proceed to give the reaſons, and then the application of the Point.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> There is a neceſſity of Faith in Prayer, becauſe we cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe pray to the Father in the Name of Chriſt; 'tis of abſolute neceſſity that wee pray in the Name of Chriſt; otherwiſe our prayers are neither acceptable to God, nor profitable to our ſelves, the acceptance and efficacy of the Saints prayers with God, turn onely upon this hinge, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend ſolely upon this <hi>ſubſtratum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.13, 14 1 Pet. 2.5 Rev. 8.3, 4</note> that they are offered up in the Name, and by the hand of Chriſt: now if they fail in this, they loſe all their work, which is but loſt labour; prayers without Faith, are prayers without fruit, becauſe they are without Chriſt: that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38145:34"/>which is Faithleſs, is Chriſtleſs, and therefore muſt needs alſo be fruitleſs, for in him is all our fruit found, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.8. Wee cannot bear any fruit by any ſpiritual ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice or ſacrifice wee tender up unto God, but in and through his Son Jeſus Chriſt. Now wee cannot pray in the Name of Chriſt, if wee do not pray in Faith; it is Faith onely that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hold of the Name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo bring our ſervices unto God by him <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.12. To pray in the Name of Chriſt, is to pray in the Faith of his Name; we may pray with the Name of Chriſt in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mouths, and yet not pray in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Name, unleſs wee pray with the Faith of Chriſt in our hearts.</p>
               <p>And obſerve it as a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and infallible Rule of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, that where-ever wee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are in Scripture commanded to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38145:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>do, or promiſed to receive any thing in the Name of Chriſt; the meaning is, that wee ſhould do and receive the ſame by Faith in his Name, and not by the bare uſe of his Name in our mouths; and to repoſe any confidence, or lay any ſtreſs upon the bare uſe of the Name of Chriſt in our mouths, any otherwiſe than wee have, and exerciſe the Faith of his Name in our hearts, is to act more like unto Conjurors, than Chriſtians; more like Sorcerers than Saints, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.13, 14, 15. <hi>Then certain of the vagabond Jews, Exorciſts, took upon them to call over them which had evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, the Name of the Lord Jeſus, ſaying, Wee adjure you by Jeſus whom Paul preacheth. And there were ſeven Sons, of one Sceva a Jew, and chief of the Prieſts, which did ſo. And the evil ſpirit anſwered and ſaid, Jeſus I know, and Paul I
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38145:35"/>know, but who are yee? And the man in whom the evil ſpirit was, leapt on them, and overcame them, &amp;c.</hi> It ſeems by this Scripture, that 'tis a peece of the Myſtical Doctrin of Necromancy, and the practice of ſorcerers, to truſt much to the virtue and power of names; but this is no part of the Doctrine of Chriſtianity, nor the practice of true Chriſtians; they do not expect to prevail with God by the Name of Chriſt in their mouths, but by the Faith of Chriſt in their hearts; here the ſeven Sons of <hi>Sceva</hi> come with the Name of Chriſt in their mouths, thinking as many carnal Chriſtians do, to do great matters by the power of that Name; but wanting the Faith of Chriſt in their hearts, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail nothing, but come off with ſhame and confuſion of face, through their miſerable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38145:35"/>expected diſappointment, and ſo will all thoſe do that truſt to their Carnal Forms, and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies, and as they ſuppoſe, moſt Excellent, and Abſolute forms of prayers, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Name of Chriſt, which they often, and in vain do take into their mouths, whilſt they have not the Faith of Chriſt in their hearts: To pray with the Name of Chriſt in the mouth, is fruitleſs and vain, where there is not the exerciſe of the Faith of Chriſt in the heart; therefore the exerciſe of Faith in prayer, is of abſolute and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible neceſſity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Becauſe wee cannot otherwiſe pray aright; 'tis the <hi>light of Faith</hi> onely by which the children of God are guided and governed in all the ſpiritual and heavenly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of Religion; the things of the Spirit, the things of eternity,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38145:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>are unſeen things, things that are notſeen by the eye of ſenſe, and natural reaſon; and the light of Faith onely, is that, by which theſe things are ſeen and made manifeſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Faith is the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> No inferiour light can be ſufficient to guide in and about thoſe things that are ſuperiour to it; the light of ſenſe being an inferiour light in man, which is common to him with the brute, is not able to guide him in and about the things of a man, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar to him as a man: as to argue and diſcourſe, by fit <hi>mediums</hi> conducing to ſuch an end; to meditate upon the works of Creation and Providence; to ſearch out the natural Cauſe, and Reaſon of things, &amp;c. To bee guided in, and about ſuch things hee muſt have, and exerciſe the light of Reaſon, which is a ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38145:36"/>light to that of Senſe, and fitted and ſuited by the wiſdom of his creator, and planted in him for ſuch an end.</p>
               <p>So alſo the light of naturall Reaſon, which is an inferiour light to that of Faith, cannot guide a man in thoſe actions and things which are Spiritual, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime, and above the reach of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, depending only upon Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation. A man by the light of Nature cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nor diſcern the things of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p>Now Prayer being a Work of the Spirit, and the things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which wee converſe with God in Prayer, being Spirituall and Heavenly things, depending upon Divine Revelation, upon the teſtimony of the Word and Spirit of God, wee muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity have a ſuperiour light to guide us in thoſe things, <hi>i.e.</hi> the,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38145:37"/>light and evidence of Faith; which is a Heavenly gift, from the father of lights, to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Kingdom, by which only, they can converſe with God, and offer up their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sacrifices and ſervices to him in a right manner. And as it is impoſſible for a man to ſee, and hear, and ſmell, and feel, and taſte, without ſenſe, or to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, diſcourſe, argue and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the natural cauſe of things, without Reaſon; ſo it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a man to Pray, Hear the Word, Receive the Seals of the Covenant, or perform any other ſpirituall duty, in a right manner without Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. Hee therefore that prayes without Faith, prayes amiſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receives not any fruit of his prayers, <hi>James</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But may not a man that hath no true Faith, make ſuch a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38145:37"/>Prayer, which for the matter of it is very good and holy, and ask ſuch petitions as are right and good, and which no man can finde fault with?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wee grant hee may; but yet ſuch an one doth ever ask a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs; for though he asketh right and good things in prayer, yet the grounds upon which he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and his ends and aims, and the frame of his heart in asking, are rotten and naught; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ever asketh amiſs, <hi>James</hi> 4.3. <hi>Yee ask and have not, becauſe yee ask amiſs;</hi> to ſpend it upon your luſts.</p>
               <p>Reaſon and common light may direct a man to ask good and right things of God in prayer; but theſe cannot help him to right grounds, to right ends and aims, and to a right frame of heart in prayer, onely the light of Faith which is influenced by the Spirit and Word of God can
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38145:38"/>do this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8, 26.27. To pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without the real exerciſe of tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Faith, is to pray in vain, becauſe ſo to pray, is to pray amiſs; there fore the exerciſe of Faith i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer is of abſolute neceſſity.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 3. Becauſe otherwiſe we can not pray with acceptation; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is the duty of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and the excellency of tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grace in every duty and hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> action, to look unto God as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ultimate and higheſt end, to have its acceptation and approbation from him in all things, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Wherefore wee labour, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſent or abſent, we may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of him.</hi> Now that is the glory of a duty, and that which crowns it with life, ſweetneſs, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy, bleſſing and honour, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it comes off with divine accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>And therefore when God the Father would put the greateſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38145:38"/>honour upon his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and crown his work with he greateſt glory, he doth it by witneſſing his approbation and acceptation thereof from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. And again, <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.5. <hi>This is my beloved Son in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hom I am well pleaſed.</hi> And where this is wanting, wee may write upon our higheſt enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and performances <hi>[Icha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bod] The glory is departed;</hi> the like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weetneſs, glory and bleſſedneſs of a duty is loſt, where this is wanting, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10. Now therefore it mainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erns us to look unto this in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur holy ſervices and ſacrifices, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they may come upon Gods Altar with acceptation; but this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annot be without Faith, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot pray with acceptation, if wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o not pray in Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>But without Faith it is impoſsible to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leaſe him.</hi> And again, <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38145:39"/>is not of Faith is ſin.</hi> So t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faithleſs prayers (like blinde a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lame ſacrifices under the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.8.) are both unaccepta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſinful; upon all which con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations it doth more than ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ficiently appear, that there is neceſſity of Faith in prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> The opening and diſcove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this great Goſpel truth, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be of uſe both to ſinners <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saints, to beleevers and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leevers, to formal hypocrit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to ſincere Chriſtians, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ther weak or ſtrong.</p>
               <p>And firſt by way of Inform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it may ſerve to inform us three things very needful a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> profitable for all men to know.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How worthleſs, vile, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſeleſs; yea how ſinful and ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> minable the prayers of all unb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leevers, wicked perſons, and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mal hypocrites are.</p>
               <p>If the efficacy, excellency an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:38145:39"/>worth of prayer dependeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, and is according to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe of Faith in it, and Faith be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he life, glory, and ſtrength of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rayer, as hath been already <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ewed; then how fruitleſs, vile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd worthleſs muſt the prayers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all unbeleevers, wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons, and formal hypocrites in the world needs be?</p>
               <p>'Tis the manner of wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons, and formal hypocrites, whoſe Religion lyes in a few ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernal ſervices and ceremonies, to glory much in their book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rayers, their ſay-prayers, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orm-prayers, which they cry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p with as much ſuperſtitious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd blinde zeal, as the <hi>Athenians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id their Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage which fell down from <hi>Jupiter, Act.</hi> 9.35. But if wee confider the perſons, who are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dmirers and Authors of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormal ſervices. The viſible
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38145:40"/>Characters of unbeleef, enmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt Chriſt, prophaneneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> godlineſs, and hypocriſie, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are ſo legible in their hearts a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lives, that hee that runs m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read them; <hi>(For out of the ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dance of the heart, the mouth ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eth.)</hi> Wee need no more to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vince and aſſure us, that the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſuch their ſervices are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worthleſs, vain, and unprofita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things, which God takes no ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſure in, and which thomſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can have no profit or fruit by. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10. Where the Lord Hoſts ſpeaking to a generati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of corrupt and ungodly Prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and People, who by their unha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lowed and unſanctified courſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had polluted his Name, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rupted his true Worſhip, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peareth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9. Tell them plainly, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſure in you, ſaith the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Hoſts, neither will I accept an offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38145:40"/>at your hand.</hi> And again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Bring no more vain oblations, Incerſe is an abomination to mee, the New-Moons, and Sabbaths, the calling of Aſſemblies I cannot away with; it is iniquity, even the ſolemn meeting. Your New Moons, and your appointed Feaſts my ſoul ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, they are a trouble unto mee, I am weary to bear them, and when yee ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you: Yea when yee make many prayers, I will not hear; Your hands are full of blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is marvellous to conſider the admirable wiſdome of the holy Spirit of God in the mouth of this holy Prophet, in cutting aſunder the very ſinews, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the very bulworks and ſtrong holds of the hypocrites confidence, ripping open their hypocriſie and falſhood to the quick, and caſting moſt contempt and holy diſdain upon thoſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38145:41"/>things wherein they do moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all glory and boaſt themſelves Of thoſe things wherein the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deal moſt proudly, doth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit ſpeak moſt contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their feſtivals, and ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſanctified holy daies, in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation whereof they place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much of their Religion, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo confidently bleſs themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how doth the Lord contem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with utmoſt diſdain? and caſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> even with loathing and hatred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Your New Moons, and yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> appointed Feaſts, my ſoul hateth they are a trouble unto mee; I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weary to bear them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Their ſervice, which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſwers to the Sacrifices of ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yea, their offerings and oblation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which they bring and perform with ſo much carnal devotion and conteſt for with ſo much blinde zeal, how doth the Lord
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38145:41"/>reject and proteſt againſt as moſt hateful and diſpleaſing to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and a burden too heavy for him to bear? <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Bring no more vain oblations, Incenſe is an abomination unto me, the calling of Aſſemblies I cannot away with; It is iniquity, even the ſolemn meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh what ſhame and confuſion will one day cover the faces of thoſe wicked and ungodly hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites? who perſecute, oppreſs, puniſh and condemn the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the righteous, becauſe they cannot in conſcience own or joyn with their Idolatrous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies? which becauſe of their number, they call ſolemn and publick, when as the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth reject and diſown them, and calls them iniquity and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; not onely wicked, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, or ungodly, but wickedneſs, and iniquity, in the abſtract; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38145:42"/>it is iniquity under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Piety; Idolatry and falſe Worſhip under a pretence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſhipping God; ſpiritual wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is the greateſt wickedneſs becauſe it hath in it the ſpirits o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wickedneſs; <hi>Simulata ſanctita</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin) duplex iniquitas &amp; quia iniquitas, &amp; quia ſimulati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i. e.</hi> feigned ſanctity is doubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iniquity, both becauſe iniquity and becauſe feigned.</p>
               <p>The Religion of Idolaters an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> falſe worſhippers, is their wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> piece; their prophaneneſs, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, curſing, drunkenneſs, exceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of riot, chambering, wantonneſs fornication, adultery, oppreſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cruelty, with all other their fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wickedneſs, is bad enough; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> Idolatry, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Will-worſhip, is wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all, and therefore called em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically, and by way of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>i. e. The unclea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:38145:42"/>thing,</hi> which the Saints of God are forbidden ſo much as to touch, as ever they expect and hope to be received and owned by God in that relation of Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Wherefore come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and be yee ſeparate, ſaith the Lord: And touch not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing, and I will receive you, and be a Father unto you, and yee ſhall be my Sons and my Daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi> Yea it is called, <hi>the abominable thing which the Lord doth hate,</hi> Jer. 44.4. <hi>Oh do not this abominable thing that I hate:</hi> Intimating that the holy God hath a ſpecial and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar hatred, abomination and deteſtation thereof above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their formal prayers, which they make and ſay over with much ignorant devotion, with all their <hi>[ſignificant]</hi> Ceremonies at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the ſame; their veſtures
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38145:43"/>and geſtures, as bowing, cringing ſpreading forth hands, &amp;c. which hypocrites do ſo much magnifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and applaud, in compariſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereof they do not only ſligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and diſ-reſpect, but alſo mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſperately, if not maliciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and blaſpheme even th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſed Spirit of Grace and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; how doth the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reject and diſown them? <hi>verſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>And when yee ſpread forth you hands, I will hide mine eyes fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you. Yea when yee make ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prayers, I will not hear. Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hands are full of blood;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as the voice from Heaven to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Graecian</hi> Tyrant) <hi>i. e. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> within,</hi> will certainly fruſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and make void all the extern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſervices and devotions of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wicked hypocrites. In whom tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scripture is perfectly fulfilled <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Hee that turneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his ear from hearing the Law, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:38145:43"/>his prayer ſhall be abomination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, This may inform us of the excellency and preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of true Faith; The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and worth of things, is to bee valued by their uſefulneſs, and the more uſefull and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a thing is, the more excellent and precious it is: Bread-corn, is a more excellent and precious thing than <hi>Bullymong</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">i.e horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn.</note>, becauſe more uſeful and neceſſary for the ſupport of mans life. And Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is more excellent and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than Rubies, becauſe more uſeful for the management of humane affairs. Grace is more excellent than Gifts, and Parts, becauſe more needfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in order to the ſouls eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal welfare. A man may bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, bee happy, and bleſſed for ever, without Gifts and Parts, but a man cannot be ſaved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Grace, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. So Faith
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38145:44"/>is a moſt excellent and preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing, becauſe ſo abundantly, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indiſpenſibly, ſo univerſally uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neceſſary for us, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this particular caſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but alſo, in all other Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſacrifices and ſervices, which wee offer up unto God through Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In all which reſpects, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scripture holds moſt true, <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6.6. <hi>Without Faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God.</hi> Wee judge of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> goodneſs and excellency of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tree, by the goodneſs of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fruit, and of the Cauſe, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Effects: So the excellency, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preciouſneſs of Faith, is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſcerned by the excellent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> precious fruits and effects the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of, in the hearts and lives of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> precious Saints.</p>
               <p>Oh! the great and glorious things which the Saints and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vants of God have been enabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:38145:44"/>and taught to do, by the ſtrength and light of Faith. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33. <hi>Who through Faith ſubdued King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, wrought righteouſneſs, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Promiſes, ſtopped the mouths of Lions, quenched the violence of fire, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, out of weakneſs was made ſtrong, waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the Armies of the Aliens; women received their dead raiſed to life again!</hi> And as the Saints and Servants of God have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to do: So alſo to ſuffer great and ſtrange things by faith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. <hi>And others were tortured, not accepting deliverance, that they might obtain a better reſurrection. And others had tryal of cruel mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſcourgings, yea moreover of bonds and impriſonment. They were ſtoned, they were ſawn aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, were tempted, were ſlain with the ſword; they wandred about in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skins, being
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38145:45"/>deſtitute, afflicted, tormented, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the invaluable and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable worth and excellency of Faith! which bringeth forth ſuch precious fruits in the hearts and lives of poor, weak, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible men and women! who are ſubject to the ſame paſſions, encompaſſed with the ſame infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, liable to the ſame temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations common to mans nature, and yet have been enabled to do and ſuffer ſuch things as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and againſt nature; requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a ſupernatural and divine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and all this by the light and ſtrength of Faith; As <hi>verſ.</hi> 39. <hi>All theſe obtained a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port through Faith. Optima ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> arbor, quae tales habet fructus!</hi> Moſt excellent doubtleſs is that Tree, which brings forth ſuch fruits: <hi>I will ſhew thee my Faith by my works,</hi> ſaith the holy man, <hi>James</hi> 2.18. Faith is a working
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38145:45"/>Grace, and it worketh like its ſelf. <hi>Operari ſequitur ad eſſe [i.e.</hi> the operation and working of things is according to the nature and being of them] is a true prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in nature, and 'tis as true al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in grace; if therefore the works of Faith be ſo excellent and glorious, oh how excellent then is the nature, the life, and eſſence of this Faith! It was the ſaying of a Heathen Philoſopher, from the obſervation which hee made of the excellent and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable works and fruits of moral virtue in the lives of ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; that if the face and image of virtue could be repreſented to the bodily eye, the beauty and glory thereof would be ſo great, that it would even raviſh the whole world; if the Heathens were ſo much taken with the beauty of morality, becauſe of the excellent fruits and effects
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38145:46"/>thereof in the lives of ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens? Oh how much more ſhould Chriſtians be taken with the beauty of Faith and Grace, becauſe of the admirable and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fruits it hath brought forth in the lives of the Saints! with which the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament do ſo much abound.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, This may inform us whence it is, and how it cometh to paſs, that oft-times the prayers even of godly and holy men, fall ſhort of Heaven, and prove not ſucceſsful for themſelves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as both Scripture and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doth teſtifie; even from hence it is, becauſe they do not alwaies pray in Faith; a good man, a precious holy man, may have the grace of Faith in his heart, and yet may want the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it, in this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſe, in this or that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38145:46"/>ordinance or duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> had the Grace of Faith in his heart, but wanted the active power and exerciſe thereof in that particular caſe of confeſſing and owning Jeſus Chriſt before men, when he was in the High Prieſts Hall, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.70, 72, 74. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> had the grace of Faith, but wanted the energy and exerciſe thereof at the water of <hi>Meribah,</hi> in that particular caſe of bringing forth water out of the Rock, onely by ſpeaking to it. And their want of Faith did appear, in that they ſmote the Rock twice, when they ſhould have but ſpoke unto it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20, 11, 12. <hi>verſes</hi> compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. The Diſciples had the grace of Faith in their hearts, and the gift of the Faith of the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but yet wanted the exerciſe thereof in that particular caſe of the childe poſſeſſed with a dumb
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38145:47"/>ſpirit, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.17, 18, 19. The two Diſciples going to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> had the grace of Faith in their hearts, but wanted the activity and comfort thereof in reference to the death, ſufferings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt from the dead, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.25, 26, 27.</p>
               <p>In all which actions thoſe holy men of God miſcarried, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of their wonted and uſual ſucceſs, becauſe they did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, <hi>i.e.</hi> they did not exerciſe Faith in thoſe particular caſes wherein the Lord did leave them to themſelves, to try and prove them, that they might more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly and experimentally know their own weakneſs, and ſo keep a more conſtant dependance upon divine aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Now as the precious and holy Servants of God (who have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as well as grace, fleſh as well as Spirit) may miſcarry in other
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38145:47"/>holy actions and duties; ſo alſo in this duty of prayer, ſo far as to miſs of that bleſſed fruit and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs therein, which at other times they finde; and hence it is, becauſe they do not alwaies pray in Faith, <hi>James</hi> 1, 5, 6, 7. <hi>If any of you lack wiſdome, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and upbraideth not, and it ſhall be given him: But let him ask in Faith, nothing wavering; for hee that wavereth, is like a wave of the Sea, driven with the wind, and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; For let not that man think that hee ſhall receive any thing of the Lord.</hi> The holy man <hi>James</hi> is now ſpeaking unto Saints, unto ſuch as hee ſuppoſed to have the grace of Faith, and yet putting them upon this great duty and work of prayer, and that in a particular caſe for wiſdome to manage their profeſſion as they ought to do, under thoſe tryals
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38145:48"/>and temptations which were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, which being a thing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary for them, and according to the revealed will of God, hee gives them aſſurance to prevail in the very thing asked, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Let him ask of God, &amp;c. And it ſhall be given him;</hi> but ſtill with this <hi>proviſo,</hi> and upon this condition, <hi>that hee ask in Faith,</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>But let him ask in Faith, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence 'tis clear, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle takes it for granted, that ſuch an one as hath true Faith, may yet fail in the exerciſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in this ordinance and duty of prayer; therefore hee ſaith, <hi>But let him ask in Faith;</hi> intimating that a godly man, a holy man may ask of God in prayer, and yet may not ask in Faith, and thereby miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry and loſe all the comfort and fruit of his asking, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Let not that man think that hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38145:48"/>any thing of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This may be for caution and warning to all the people of God;
<note n="2" place="margin">Uſe Caution.</note> whether they be ſtrong in Faith, or weak in Faith; whether their grace be little or much, to beware and take heed that they neglect not to ſtir up, and put in exerciſe, that grace which they have, as in all other holy duties, ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this great duty and work of prayer.</p>
               <p>The Exhortation of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> in reference to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial gift, may be applyed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian in reference to his grace, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Wherefore I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtir up the gift that is in thee, by putting on of my hands.</hi> A man may have excellent gifts and parts, and yet the Church of God bee never the better for them, unleſs thoſe gifts be ſtirred up, and kept in exerciſe: Yea a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38145:49"/>man may in time loſe his gifts by neglecting the exerciſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of them, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29. <hi>But unto him that hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (i.e. exerciſeth and improvet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not, as is clear by the ſcope o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Parable) <hi>ſhall be taken a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> even that which hee hath.</hi> So man may have true grace, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> very great meaſure of it, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may in ſome particular caſes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> under the enjoyment of mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> precious Ordinances, and in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> performance of moſt holy duties be altogether fruitleſs and u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> profitable, both to himſelf an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others, through not exerciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and ſtirring up the grace which hee hath: Yea hee may (thought not utterly loſe) yet greath weaken and impoveriſh his grace <hi>Rev.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 11.26 1 Joh. 3.9. &amp; 5.18.</note> 3.2.</p>
               <p>O Chriſtian, know, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life and comfort of thy ſoul un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the moſt precious ordinances
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38145:49"/>and in the performance of holy duties, whether with thy ſelf, or with others, lyeth not ſo much in thy having of true grace, in thy having of Faith, but in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of grace, and in the exerciſe of that Faith which thou haſt. Oh therefore beware and take heed that thou neglecteſt not to ſtir up, to keep in exerciſe thy grace, as ever thou deſireſt that thy ſoul ſhould thrive and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per under the holy ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, and be filled with joy and peace in beleeving.</p>
               <p>The life of Ordinances, the ſweetneſs of the Word and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the comfort and fruit of holy duties is loſt, when once the exerciſe of Faith is loſt! take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the exerciſe of Faith out of the heart of a Chriſtian, and what are the moſt pure and powerful ordinances, the moſt ſweet and precious Promiſes, the moſt holy
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38145:50"/>and heavenly duties, when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with the greateſt exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal excellency, but as ſo many empty Pipes, as ſo many broken Ciſterns, which can hold no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</p>
               <p>And therefore it is that the Devil doth ſo induſtriouſly tempt the Saints of God to ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſlumber and ſecurity, that ſo hindering the exerciſe of their grace, hee may deprive them o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpiritual fruit and comfort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all Gods Ordinances;
<note place="margin">☞</note> and there upon tempt them to doubt and queſtion whether they be his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances or no: and at length (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they be not ſincere) prevaile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with them to caſt off ordinance as fruitleſs and unprofitable, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to caſt reproach and dirt upon them, whereas indeed the fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is in their own hearts, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Micah</hi> 2.7. And hereupon hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Devil taken advantage to for
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38145:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe curſed tares, and corrupt opinions of Non-Ordinances, Ranters, Quakers, &amp;c. all which, though they differ among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet do agree in this, to caſt all the dirt and reproach they can upon the precious and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt: And this hath the Devil done whilſt Profeſſors were fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and had loſt the life, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, and activity of their grace, as it is written, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.25. <hi>But while men ſlept, his enemy came and ſowed tares among the Wheat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The preaching of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Act. 26.18 Eph. 4.12 Rom. 1.16</note> it is a moſt precious and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Converſion, Edification, and Salvation of the ſouls of men; but this Goſpel may bee preached clearly, powerfully, and faithfully preached, &amp; yet thoſe unto whom it is preached, have no fruit, no profit by it, for want
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38145:51"/>of Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. <hi>But the Word preached, did not profit them, not being mixed with Faith in them that heard it.</hi> Oh therefore when thou goeſt to hear the Word preached, Chriſtian, beware that thou ſtirreſt up the grace that is in thee, and in particular, this grace of Faith, without which the Word preached will not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not profit thy ſoul, though the Apoſtles themſelves, yea though an Angel from Heaven ſhould be the Preacher! The fruit and benefit of the Word preached, doth not depend ſo much upon the grace and gifts of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as upon the Faith of the hearer!</p>
               <p>So likewiſe prayer, it is a moſt precious and powerful ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, for the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things that wee ſtand in need of at the hands of God. The text it ſelf ſpeaks ſufficiently
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38145:51"/>unto this point, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. <hi>And all things whatſoever yeeſhall ask in prayer, beleeving, yee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</hi> And upon this very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration ſome have called prayer the Key of Heaven; but Faith is the hand which turns this Key. Look therefore as the Key without the hand to turn it is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; ſo prayer without Faith is fruitleſs; thou mayeſt therefore, Chriſtian, pray, and bee much in prayer, and yet loſe all thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, unleſs thou acteſt thy Faith in prayer; thou mayeſt bring thy Key of prayer to the gate of Heaven, and yet finde it faſt lockt againſt thee, unleſs thou haſt a hand of Faith to turn this Key. Oh therefore beware and take heed that thou neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not to ſtir up, and exerciſe thy Faith in prayer. Oh how many praying-daies, and faſting-daies have been loſt to the people of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38145:52"/>God, for want of Faith? which onely guides us aright in prayer, gives us a right frame of heart, and right ends and aims in prayer, as hath been already ſhewed? 'Tis a great Scripture which wee have in <hi>Zechariah,</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.5. <hi>When yee faſted and mourned in the fifth and ſeventh month, even thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty years, did yee at all faſt unto mee, even unto mee?</hi> Here wee have a praying people, who were abundant and conſtant in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ſeventy years together, and that in the moſt ſolemn and ſtrict manner, joyning faſting with their praying, and yet not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God therein, nor at all profited thereby; and the reaſon is hinted; they did not pray with a right frame of heart; they had not right ends and aims in their prayers; <hi>Did yee faſt at all unto mee, even unto mee?</hi> and whence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38145:52"/>was it that they thus miſcarried in prayer, and had not true, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, holy, and right ends and aims in prayer, but from hence, that they prayed not in Faith; they wanted the light and life of Faith, and were not guided by the Word in their faſting and praying, and ſo praying amiſs, loſt all their labour, <hi>James</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But how doth it appear that they prayed not in Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They looked not unto the word ſpoken by the former Prophets, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. therefore they prayed not in Faith; 'tis by Faith that wee look unto the Word of God, ſo as to make it our rule; now they obeyed not the Word, and therfore prayed not in Faith.</p>
               <p>Oh therefore Chriſtian, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thou faileſt not in this, in the exerciſe and activity of thy Faith in prayer; thou hadſt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fail in any thing than in this;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38145:53"/>thou hadſt better fail in the gift of prayer; thou hadſt better fail of words in prayer; thou hadſt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fail of the wiſdome and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of ſpeech in prayer; thou hadſt better fail of affection in prayer, than to fail of Faith in prayer; other defects and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities will bee paſſed by and covered,
<note place="margin">Jam. 5.17. Heb. 11.6.</note> where Faith is active<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but all other accompliſhments and ſeeming excellencies, will be deſpiſed where Faith is wanting; 'tis better for a man to want cloathes, and all outward orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the body, than to want life; life is the glory and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the creature; the pooreſt and moſt contemptible creature which hath life, is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than the moſt glorious crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that wants it; hence faith <hi>Solemon, A living Dog is better than a dead Lion.</hi> Faith is the life of prayer, the glory, the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38145:53"/>the ſtrength of Prayer; Other things are but the Ornaments of Prayer: Oh Chriſtian! look not ſo much to the Ornaments, as to the Life of thy holy duties, leſt God reject them as a dead carcaſſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note n="3" place="margin">Uſe Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> This may bee profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for Exhortation,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Unto Sinners.</p>
               <p>If there bee ſuch a neceſſity of Faith in Prayer, that without it wee cannot Pray, either accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to God, or profitably to our ſelves or others, as hath been at large declared and proved; then doth it nearly concern every ſoul yet in the ſtate of Nature, and ſhut up, or concluded under un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief (as all unregenerate perſons are, whether they bee Jews or Gentiles, Chriſtians or Heathens, Prophane perſons or Profeſſors, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.9.) to get out of that condition, and to labour for true ſaving Faith in Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:38145:54"/>
               <p>'Tis true, Faith is a Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Grace,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.40. Epheſ. 2.8</note> which grows not in Natures Garden, 'tis neither in the freedom of mans will to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, nor in the ability of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, to work Grace, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and bring forth a work of true Saving Faith in himſelf: but as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>It is God which worketh in you, both to will and to do, of his good pleaſure.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.7. Joh. 6.27. Phil. 1.12.</note> Nevertheleſs, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, it is thy duty to ſtrive in the uſe of all holy means, and to look up unto God, through Chriſt, both to incline thy will and to give thee power from heaven, to do his will. The Miller cannot command a wind but hee can ſpread the Sails, and wait upon the Providence of God for a gale; <hi>The wind blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where it liſteth, ſo is every o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that is born of the Spirit, Joh.</hi> 3.8. And if thou deſireſt to bee bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:38145:54"/>again, thou muſt wait for thoſe gales, and thou muſt wait in the uſe of means: And there is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bleſſing promiſed to them that do ſo, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34, 35. The Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man cannot command the Clouds, but hee may obſerve the ſeaſon, prepare the Earth, and ſow the precious feed,
<note place="margin">Jam. 5.7.</note> and then patiently wait for the early and the latter Rain, and he finds at Harveſt, his labour is not in vain.</p>
               <p>There is a connexion, though not of Cauſality, yet of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentality, of the end to the means, of mercy to duty, of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to practiſe, of the Harveſt to the Seed-time; of Glory to Grace, of Grace to the means of Grace; As ever therefore thou wouldeſt attain the end, which is Salvation, thou muſt uſe the means: Hee that will aſcend to the laſt, or higheſt ſtaffe of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38145:55"/>Ladder muſt begin at the firſt.</p>
               <p>O therefore, gratifie not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Devil, and thy own unregene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will, with ſuch cavilling, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhifting, but ſet upon the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in good earneſt; up and bee d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ing, and the Lord ſhall bee with thee. And aſſure thy ſelf, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it may prove difficult and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> labour, yet it will not prove loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> labour, <hi>John</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for the meat which periſheth, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for that meat which endureth un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> everlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But perhaps the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner will ſay, How ſhall I come by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> How ſhall I obtain it? What aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance have I, that if I labour f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this meat, I ſhall have any fruit of my labour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> O yes, there is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed promiſe joyned to this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, hee that bids thee labour, doth promiſe thee thy labor ſhall not be in vain; and therefore it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38145:55"/>is added; <hi>Which the Son of man ſhall give unto you, for him hath God the Father ſealed.</hi> Oh ſinner, know, that God the Father hath ſealed, <hi>i.e.</hi> ordained and anointed Jeſus Chriſt, and conſtituted him under the broad Seal of Heaven, to be the Mediator of the everlaſting Covenant, and to diſpenſe and give out all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and heavenly gifts and bleſſings therefore, unto all ſuch as the Father hath given to him, and by virtue of that donation ſhall come to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2. <hi>As thou haſt given him power over all fleſh, that hee ſhould give eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life to as many as thou hast given him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But thou wilt ſay, how ſhall I know whether I bee one of thoſe whom the Father hath given to Jeſus Chriſt? And that if I do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome unto him, I ſhall be received? Oh I am afraid that Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38145:56"/>will not receive ſuch a ſinner as am, ſuch a wretch as I am; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo vile and wretched, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hee will rather reject and caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> out as a Reprobate, as a veſſel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wrath, than receive mee unto gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> and favour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou art one of thoſe, whom th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father hath given to Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy coming to him, and cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with him in the Word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpel; for none but ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſſibly come to him,
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.44</note> ſo as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive life from him; thou ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not know before-hand that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> art given by the Father to Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, but thou muſt firſt co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unto Chriſt; and then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mayeſt know that the Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath given thee to him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou comeſt unto Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hee hath aſſured thee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Word, that hee will not reje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thee, hee will not caſt thee o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:38145:56"/>how vile or wretched ſoever thou beeſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>All that the Father giveth mee ſhall come to mee, and him that cometh unto mee, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Oh it is a bleſſed word; <hi>[In no wiſe, in no wiſe caſt out]</hi> what-ever thy cauſe or condition be, though never ſo deſperate in thine own eye, yet if thou comeſt unto him, he will in no wiſe caſt thee out.</p>
               <p>And thou haſt the bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents and experiences of many great ſinners, who upon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and coming unto Jeſus Chriſt by Faith, have obtained mercy, and are now glorified Saints in Heaven; witneſs <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh,</hi> who uſed witchcraft and inchantments, who ſhed much innocent blood, and filled <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> with blood, and made a whole Nation to ſin, and yet when in his affliction he humbled himſelf greatly, and ſought unto
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38145:57"/>the Lord, hee obtained mercy, and hee that had been before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wicked Necromancer, a Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a Murderer, an abominable Idolater, hath now obtained mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, becomes a New Creature old things are paſſed away with him, and all things are beco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> new, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.1,—20. <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Magdalen</hi> was a very great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<note place="margin">Mark 16.9 Luke 8.2</note> out of whom Chriſt had ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeven Devils, and yet ſhee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, and when ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> came unto Jeſus Chriſt, hee di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not caſt her out: So likewiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> was a great ſinner befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Converſion, a perſecutor, a bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and injurious, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hee obtained mercy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>And wherefore did the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſingle out theſe great and chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinners, and make them object<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his ſaving grace and favour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but that in them hee might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit a pattern of his glorio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:38145:57"/>grace, for the encouragement of other great ſinners (not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſin, with a preſumption of finding mercy at the laſt) but to repent, and turn, and come in to his Son Jeſus Chriſt, that they may be ſaved; So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Howbeit (ſaith Paul) for this cauſe I obtained mercy, that in mee firſt Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long ſuffering for a pattern to them, which ſhould hereafter beleeve on him to life everlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this know, poor ſinner, <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> oh therefore be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, becauſe thou art a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but hearken to the call of Chriſt, in the voice of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and know, that thou art cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this day by this word of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; to labour for Faith in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo thou mayeſt be in a capacity of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38145:58"/>performing this holy duty of prayer,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6</note> and other holy duties, ſo as to pleaſe God in the doing of them, which without Faith thou canſt not do.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But what ſhall I do in the mean time? ſhall I neglect prayer, becauſe I cannot in my natural and unbeleeving eſtate pleaſe God in what I do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, oh no, thou art commanded to pray, to call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Name of the Lord; prayer is a natural duty, written upon every mans conſcience; the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation whereof cannot bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with, by any power, or under any pretence whatſoever, thou muſt not therefore caſt of prayer, that ſo thou mayeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in thy ſin and unbeleef; but thou muſt caſt off thy ſin and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo thou mayeſt continue in prayer, which if thou neglecteſt, thou art guilty
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38145:58"/>of a three-fold Robbery.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thou robbeſt God of his glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thy own ſoul, body and family of the mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thy Neighbour of the charity of thy prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was in the gall of bitterneſs, and yet <hi>Peter</hi> bids him pray, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.23. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hee bids him repent alſo: <hi>Repent therefore of this thy wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and pray to God.</hi> Therefore a wicked man, a man in the gall of bitterneſs muſt pray. But withall hee muſt repent of his wickedneſs, and beleeve, that through Chriſt Jeſus, remiſſion and forgiveneſs of his ſin, may be obtained; and upon this ground of Repentance and Faith in Chriſt, the Apoſtle bids him to pray: <hi>If peradventure, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:38145:59"/>
               <p>Secondly, Unto Saints.</p>
               <p>Oh yee precious Saints of God, who have this precious Faith, this precious ſeed of God beſtowed upon you in Jeſus Chriſt, to whom it is given to beleeve in the name of Jeſus; unto you doth this word of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation ſpeak, as unto Sons and Daughters. Oh be not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but beleeving, exert, and put forth this Heaven-born prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and ſeed of Faith into exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe; let it not lye by you as a dead drug, when there is ſuch quick trading at the throne of Grace. Great Merchants will empty their Ware houſes, and bring forth their richeſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity when they have a quick trade, when the wants and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of their own or other Countries, do give them advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to put off with greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; they will uſe the utmoſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38145:59"/>and induſtry, and will lay out themſelves to the utmoſt; they will venture all their ſtock, engage all their credit, improve all their intereſt in ſuch a ſeaſon: Shall men be ſo wiſe for earth, and ſhall not the children of the Kingdome be as wiſe for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</p>
               <p>O yee Saints of God, yee are the heavenly Merchants; who onely have this trade in your hands; yee have intereſt in the heavenly Country, and ye have a Factor there, who is both able and faithful, who will not fail to put off your prayers with the beſt advantage, and procure you returns in the richeſt and beſt things of the Country, which ſhall beſt anſwer your intereſt and profit here on earth. And now yee have a moſt precious ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The wants and neceſſities of three great Nations (whereof
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38145:60"/>your ſelves are a part, and in the peace whereof your peace is bound up) do call aloud for the help of your prayers, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as great ſymptomes and tokens of divine diſpleaſure, and under as black a cloud of ſtormy wrath, as any Nation wee read of in all the Word of God; ſearch the Scriptures, and take a cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of all the characters and marks expreſſed there of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration marked out for vengeance; and try if they be not all found upon this generation, this one excepted. That the Lord of Hoſts hath reſerved unto himſelf a remnant. And can you ſee all this and be ſilent? have yee not ſo much charity, ſo much bowels of compaſſion for your native Country,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.22</note> your children and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, as <hi>Abraham</hi> had for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</hi> as <hi>Lot</hi> for <hi>Zoar?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The deſolations of Mount
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38145:60"/>
                  <hi>Zion,</hi> the captivity of Gods Ark, the afflictions and troubles that are accompliſhed in your dear brethren, who are like ſheep appointed for the ſlaughter, do call aloud for your moſt fervent prayers, and ſtrong cryes, to bee ſent up to Heaven inceſſantly, &amp; that you give the Lord no reſt till hee doth ariſe, and have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon <hi>Zion,</hi> and turn the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of his people as ſtreams in the South: Can yee bee at eaſe in <hi>Zion,</hi> and not regard the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of <hi>Joſeph?</hi> Can yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Zion</hi> in travel, yea crying out, and in pangs, to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not lend a helping hand?</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ruinous caſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of thouſands of precious ſouls, who are like to periſh for want of viſion, to ſtarve for want of the bread of life; who wander from mountain to hill to ſeek the Word of the Lord, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38145:61"/>finde it; who cry out for bread, and behold ſtones are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them inſtead of bread, who ask for fiſh, but are fed with Scorpions; who ſeek water, but finde none, and their tongue faileth for thirſt; do alſo in their deep miſery and diſtreſs cry out and call aloud to you; oh pray the Lord of the harveſt, that he would ſend forth labourers, &amp; drive out loiterers; that hee would raiſe up unto us a ſoul-ſearching &amp; a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaving Miniſtry, and take away from us the heavy ſcourge and plague of a ſoul-murdering, blind and ſuperſtitious Clergy; for where the blind lead the blind, both muſt fall into the ditch.</p>
               <p>Oh yee Saints of God, who only know the worth of ſouls, who only can be truly ſenſible of ſpiritual evils, and know both the worth and want of a true Goſpel-Miniſtry; can ye be ſilent and ſee
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38145:61"/>ſuch merchandize made of the ſouls of men, by the greedy Merchants of <hi>Babylon?</hi> Never was there a time, from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world, in which the Saints had more advantage of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and eminent ſervice by prayer for the poor Nations of the earth, and for their dear bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in ſufferings, and for the ſouls of men! yea and for the whole Creation, than at this day! In which the Nations of the earth are ſo greatly diſtreſſed, the minds of men perplexed, and their hearts even failing them for fear, and for looking after the things that are coming to paſs on the earth; yea <hi>the whole Creation groaneth and travelleth in pain, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be delivered from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God.</hi> In which <hi>Zions</hi> conſolation, and <hi>Babylons</hi> confuſion greatly haſteneth; the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38145:62"/>time of <hi>Babels</hi> Tyranny, and the Saints captivity, is ſo near fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the times of refreſhing a coming from the preſence of the Lord, and the time of the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things: Oh ye Saints of God know that this is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſeaſon; let but your prayers meet together in the Angels hand, who ſtands before the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar to offer them up with his own Incenſe, and then great and marvellous things will be done in the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3, 4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:38145:62"/>
               <head>THE Efficacy of FAITH IN PRAYER.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 21.22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And all things whatſoever yee ſhall ask in Prayer, beleeving, yee ſhall receive,</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He next thing obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in the Text, and propoſed to be handled in this Treatiſe, is
<q>The Efficacy of Faith in Prayer.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Faith is a plenipotentiary grace, it hath a kind of omnipotency in it, it cometh with a full commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38145:63"/>from Heaven, to the poor Diſciples of Chriſt on earth, by which they may do and obtain great things with God; yea all things whatſoever they ſhall ask in prayer, they ſhall obtain by Faith. The great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will not, cannot deny any thing to his poor ſervants here on earth, which they ask in Faith. Hee is faithful who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and cannot deny himſelf; the word is gone out of his mouth in righteouſneſs, and hee will not repent, hee will not call it in again. <hi>And all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever yee ſhall ask in prayer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, yee ſhall receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh here is a large commiſſion indeed! <hi>All things! and all things whatſoever.</hi> Here are no limits, no bounds ſet to Faith in prayer! Faith may ask what it will, and have what it asks at the hand of God! Faith
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38145:63"/>can but ask and have! Faith doth but ſpeak the word on Earth, and it is done in Heaven! the truth is, Faith is a modeſt grace, a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, wiſe and ſober grace, that looketh at the will of God as her Rule, and the glory of God as her ultimate end and aim in all things, and therefore will not, cannot deſire or ask any thing contrary to Gods moſt holy will, or croſs to, and inconſiſtent with his glory; and therefore Faith hath the Key of Heaven committed to her, and may go to the heap of mercy, and take e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven what ſhee will, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.28. <hi>O Woman great is thy Faith, be it unto thee even as thou wilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Efficacy of Faith in prayer, and the mighty prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power it hath with God, is ſufficiently made manifeſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the truth of Gods moſt holy Word and Promiſes.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:38145:64"/>
               <p n="2">2. In the Saints moſt precious and conſtant Experiences.</p>
               <p>The truth of Gods moſt holy Word and Promiſes,
<note n="1" place="margin">The truth of Gods holy word and promiſes.</note> do abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly atteſt and bear witneſs to the mighty efficacy of Faith i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer; great things are promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yea all things are promiſed to the prayers of Faith. So in the Text: <hi>And all things whatſoever yee ſhall ask in prayer, beleeving yee ſhall receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Word of Chriſt, this is a gracious Promiſe of Jeſus Chriſt to his Diſciples here on earth, and hee will be as good as his word; hee is the faithful witneſs, and the truth it ſelf, and therefore hee cannot lye, he can as well ceaſe to be God, as ceaſe to be true and faithful in his Word and Promiſes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>For all the Promiſes of God in him are Yea, and in him Amen,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> truth and aſſurance, or moſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38145:64"/>ſure and ſtedfaſt] <hi>unto the glory of God by us;</hi> So that God ſtands upon the truth of his Word and Promiſes, as a great part of his glory, and hee will have the glory of his truth, what-ever comes of it, hee will appear to be true in his Word and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yea in all his Promiſes to a jot and tittle, there ſhall not the leaſt jot or tittle thereof fail, till all be fulfilled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. <hi>For verily I ſay unto you, till Heaven and Earth paſs, one jot, or one tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſs from the Law, till all bee fulfilled:</hi> As if the Lord had ſaid, yee are apt to ſet light by my Word, to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and doubt of the truth and certainty thereof; but I aſſure you, I ſtand ſo much upon my Word, to have it fulfilled and made good to the utmoſt, that if Heaven and Earth lay in one ſcale, and the leaſt iota or tittle
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38145:65"/>of my Word in the other, I would rather ſuffer Heaven and Earth (<hi>i. e.</hi> the whole Creation) to periſh and come to nothing, than that the leaſt iota or tittle of my Word ſhould fail, till all be fulfilled. So wonderfully doth the God of Truth ſtand upon his glory in this reſpect; therefore all the Promiſes of God in him (<hi>i. e.</hi> in Chriſt) are yea, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him amen, becauſe this is for the glory of God, to be as good as his word, and not to falſifie, but to fulfill all his Promiſes.</p>
               <p>Now many exceeding great and precious promiſes hath Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made in Chriſt unto his people praying in Faith, or exerciſing Faith in prayer. Wee ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in one or two, in liew of all the reſt; which being added to this of the Text, may bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to give a full teſtimony to the truth in hand; that ſo in the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38145:65"/>mouth of two or three witneſſes, this word may bee eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>The firſt that we ſhall inſtance in, is, that great Charter of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or promiſe made to the poor afflicted, tempted, and deſpiſed Saints, and Churches of Chriſt here on earth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.19. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I ſay unto you, that if two of you ſhall agree on earth, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing that they ſhall ask, it ſhall bee done for them of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The number of true Diſciples is in many places very ſmall, it may bee two of a Family, and one of a Tribe; and the true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt, are for the moſt part but ſmall, and few in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: eſpecially compared with the falſe Church, and Churches of Antichriſt, the Whore that ſitteth upon many Waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15. But O yee Saints and Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, let not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38145:66"/>the paucity, and ſmalneſs of your number diſcourage you, though the malice and rage of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, may like the great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-floods, keep good Neighbors one from another, ſo that ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſſemble and meet together in that ſolemn and publick man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as yee could deſire: yet bee not diſcouraged, do not think the Efficacy and ſtrength of Prayer, is thereby ſo diminiſhed, or weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that yee cannot prevail in Heaven:
<note place="margin">Col 25</note> 
                  <hi>You may bee preſent in Spirit, when abſent in body.</hi> Your Prayers may meet in Heaven, when your perſons cannot meet upon Earth.
<note place="margin">Rev. 8.3</note> 
                  <hi>You may bee caſt into Priſons, and Dungeons,</hi> you may bee ſcattered, and wander in the deſart places, in the dens and caves of the earth, but here is your comfort, Heaven is ſtill o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</p>
               <p>And let mee tell you from
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38145:66"/>this Scripture; yee may do and obtain great things in Heaven <hi>(If two of you ſhall agree on earth, as touching any thing they ſhall ask. it ſhall be done for you in Heaven.) If two of you ſhall agree;</hi> 'tis not meant in a way of worldly poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and carnal contrivance, but in a way of ſpiritual harmony and conſent of ſoul ariſing from the unity of Faith, and the anointing of the Spirit,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.27</note> teaching and guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you in prayer, to ask thoſe things which are according to the will of God: let the thing be what it will, ask it in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above, or in the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath; let it be never ſo hard and difficult, and in the eye of fenſe and reaſon even impoſſible, yet it ſhall certainly be done for you, and granted in Heaven. Oh what a bleſſed charter! what a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty is this, granted to the children of God, that by Faith
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38145:67"/>in prayer here on earth, they may have any thing, even what they will, done for them in Heaven!</p>
               <p>And this is the priviledge of all thoſe little ones, that beleeve in Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. and 14. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20. This is not the priviledge of old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſtrong men onely, but even of babes in Chriſt, ſuch as are little ones, little in the worlds account, and it may be little in the eye of other Saints, but leaſt of all in their own eye; yet theſe little ones that beleeve in Chriſt, how contemptible, little and low ſoever they be on earth, are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, great and high in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and may do ſuch things by Faith in prayer, as the greateſt Monarchs and Princes upon Earth cannot do by their greateſt force and power: As will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear in the ſecond Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and word of Promiſe, which
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38145:67"/>for the proof the point, wee ſhall alſo a little inſiſt upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 45.11. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, the holy one of Iſrael, and his Maker. Ask mee of things to come, concerning my Sons, and concerning the work of my hands, command yee mee.</hi> Oh the admirable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite condeſcention of the great <hi>Jehovah!</hi> who hath created the Heavens, and formed the Earth, and commandeth all the hoſts of them! That hee who command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Angels, and ruleth in the Armies of Heaven; and in the Kingdomes of men, ſhould ſuffer himſelf to be commanded by a hand-full of poor praying-ſouls here on earth! and to have ſuch power in Heaven, as to command and diſpoſe of the great works of providence; yea the choiſeſt and moſt admirable operations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which for their rarity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency are (by way of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency)
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38145:68"/>the works of Gods hands (as the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Magicians ſaid of that rare and admirable work of Gods ſingular power and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in turning all the duſt of the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> into Lice at the word of his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> which the Magicians could not do by their inchantments, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.19. <hi>This is the finger of God!</hi>) Yet ſo it is, that a hand-full of Gods praying <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which come in Faith, to enquire and ask of God concerning his Sons and Daughters, may even command what they will, may ask and have the greateſt mercies, the moſt ſignal deliverances, and the moſt wonderful revolutions of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that the hands, <hi>i. e.</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite power of God is able to produce, and bring to paſs. As that was a moſt wonderful revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of providence, that cauſed even all the earth to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38145:68"/>even the ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected downfall of the mighty Kingdome of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in order to the ſalvation and deliverance of Gods Church and people, who there were holden in ſo ſtrong captivity, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. from the 3. <hi>v.</hi> to the 28.</p>
               <p>Oh ye precious praying-ſouls, upon whom the Lord hath pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication,
<note place="margin">Zech. 12.10, 11, 12</note> that yee may ſee him whom yee have pierced, and mourn and be in bitterneſs for your own ſins, and the ſins of the Nation; mourning even eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry family apart, the men apart, and their wives apart. Oh know, that if yee come with an humble ſenſe of your own, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſins, and with Faith in God through Jeſus Chriſt, to plead his precious promiſes, and ask of him things to come concerning his Sons and Daughters, ye may
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38145:69"/>even <hi>command</hi> what yee will (if it be a work of Gods hands, which hee hath decreed in Heaven, and declared on Earth to bring to paſs in due time,
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.2</note> as hee hath the confuſion of myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſalvation of his ſpiritual <hi>Zion</hi>) I ſay, if it be a work of his hands, <hi>i.e.</hi> within the power of his glorious arm, and infinite wiſdome, to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as moſt certainly all things propheſied and fore-told in the Word of God are; then ye need not to ſtagger, ye need not to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate about the matter, either becauſe of your own unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the great amazing diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in the way of the promiſe; but come boldly to the throne of grace, and ask in Faith, and there is nothing in Heaven or Earth too good or too great for God to do for you; ask and ſpare not, yea ſpeak the word and it ſhall be done, command with an humble
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38145:69"/>boldneſs, and it ſhall be brought forth; ask it in the Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, or in the earth beneath; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the glorious works and operations of Gods hands, chuſe where yee will, ask what yee will, and it ſhall be done for you. <hi>Ask mee things to come concerning my Sons, and concerning the works of my hands, command yee mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt precious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant experiences of the Saints and ſervants of God in all ages and generations of the world do alſo abundantly declare the mighty prevailing power and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of Faith in prayer;
<note n="2" place="margin">In the Saints ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences.</note> by which</p>
               <p n="1">1. They have prevailed with God for the turning away of his fierce wrath and anger from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Nations, who had provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him greatly, and yet periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, becauſe ſome of Gods
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38145:70"/>faithful ſervants ſtood up in the gap, and made interceſſion for them.</p>
               <p>Thus holy <hi>Moſes</hi> prevaileth with God for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they provoked him to wrath with their own inventions, and turned the glory of God into the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a Calf that eateth Hay, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.7. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, Go get thee down, for the people which thou broughteſt out of the Land of Egypt, have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted themſelves; they have turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſide quickly out of the way which I commanded them; they have made them a molten Calf, and have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped it, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Now therefore, let mee alone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them, and that I may conſume them, and I will make of thee a great Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is an ungodly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful Nation, that have great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoked the Lord by their
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:38145:70"/>Idolatry and Apoſtacy, after all thoſe wonders of mercy, which hee had wrought for them in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and at the Red Sea, which was a great aggravation of their wickedneſs, that they ſo quickly forgat God their Saviour, and turned aſide to other Gods, and gave the glory of all their deliverances and ſalvations, which <hi>Jehovah</hi> had wrought for them, unto a baſe, deteſtable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, the Image of a Calf that eateth Hay: So <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>They have made a Molten Calf, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped it, and have ſacrificed thereunto, and ſaid, Theſe be thy Gods, O Iſrael, which have brought thee up out of the Land of Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here wee have a jealous, offended and provoked God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing upon the Mount to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> as conſuming fire, taking up thoughts of wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> even to their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:38145:71"/>utter deſtruction and confuſion: <hi>Now therefore, let mee alone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them, and that I may conſume them, and I will make of thee a great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But withall, behold a wonder of infinite condeſcention, <hi>God ſtooping to man, the great Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> courting and intreating a poor, weak, ſinful man, to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and let him alone in the progreſs and execution of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt <hi>Iſrael! Let mee alone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them:</hi> As if <hi>Moſes</hi>'s prayers did tye up the hands of God, ſo that hee could not do any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> without <hi>Moſes</hi>'s leave!</p>
               <p>Oh that a poor ſinful man, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, ſhould have ſuch power with the great and holy God! yet ſuch is the efficacy of Faith in prayer, that God will
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38145:71"/>not, cannot do any thing againſt the prayers of his people, when they ask in Faith.</p>
               <p>But now doth <hi>Moſes</hi> let God alone, and ceaſe to pray, and make interceſſion for <hi>Iſrael?</hi> is <hi>Moſes</hi> content to accept the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed increaſe of his own private family, with ſo great diſhonour to the Name of God, and the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal ruine of his Church and People? No verily: The Faith and Zeal of this holy man <hi>Moſes,</hi> like a mighty fire, being a little reſtrained, breaketh forth into the greater flames. And hee ſets upon the work of prayer and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for <hi>Iſrael</hi> with the more Faith and fervent Zeal, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13. <hi>And Moſes beſought the Lord his God, and ſaid; Lord, why doth thy wrath wax hot againſt thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which thou haſt brought forth out of the Land of Egypt, with great power, and with a mighty hand?
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:38145:72"/>Wherefore ſhould the Egyptians ſpeak and ſay, for miſchief did hee bring them out, to ſlay them in the mountains, and to conſume them from the face of the earth? Turn from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this evil againſt thy People. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Abraham, Iſaac and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael thy ſervants, to whom th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſwareſt by thine own ſelf, and ſaid unto them, I will multiply your ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as the ſtars of Heaven, and all this Land that I have ſpoken of, will I give unto your ſeed, and they ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inherit it for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh here is a prayer of Faith indeed! here is much Faith acted by <hi>Moſes</hi> in this prayer; looking to the Word and Promiſe of God made to <hi>Abraham, Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> as his rule in asking, and the glory of the Name of God, as his great and ultimate end, and by good argument and ſtrength of reaſon ſhewing, that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38145:72"/>to execute his fierce wrath in conſuming his people, would neither conſiſt with his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Promiſe, nor with the glory of his own great Name, and therefore prayes the Lord to turn from his fierce wrath, and repent of this evil againſt his people.</p>
               <p>And by this prayer of Faith he prevails with God, and delivers <hi>Iſrael</hi> from that conſuming wrath and anger of God that was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt them, ſo that they periſhed not in their iniquity, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>And the Lord repented of the evil which hee thought to do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which famous prayer and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> is recorded in the book of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the onely means of <hi>Iſraels</hi> preſervation from the conſuming power of <hi>Jehovahs</hi> great wrath and fierce anger, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106, 23.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38145:73"/>
                  <hi>Therefore hee ſaid that hee would deſtroy them; had not Moſes his choſen ſtood before him in the breach to turn away his wrath leſt he ſhould deſtroy them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the prevailing power and efficacy of Faith in prayer! that by one prayer of Faith, a whole Nation ſhould be delivered from ſo great a ruine!</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> Thus alſo righteous <hi>Lot</hi> by one prayer of Faith delivered <hi>Zoar</hi> from the common deſtruction and over throw of <hi>Sodom</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> that very morning when fire was ready to come down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to deſtroy thoſe Cities, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.18. <hi>And Lot ſaid unto them; oh not ſo my Lord, Behold now thy ſervant hath found grace in thy ſight, and thou hast magnified thy mercy which thou haſt ſhewed unto mee in ſaving my life, and I cannot eſcape to the mountain, leſt ſome evil take mee and I dye. Behold
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38145:73"/>now, this City is near to flee unto, and it is a little one. O let me eſcape thither (is it not a little one) and my ſoul ſhall live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This prayer of <hi>Lot</hi> was not without ſome viſible tincture of humane frailty, and weakneſs of Faith, wherein hee offended in that hee accepted not the place which the Lord had appointed, but chuſeth another, aſcribing more to the place, than to the power and good pleaſure of God for his protection. Nevertheleſs it being a prayer of Faith, in which there was a real exerciſe of Faith, in that hee beleeved God was able to ſpare <hi>Zoar,</hi> and to make it a means of his preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and more comfortable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving than the deſolate moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and therefore prayes that the Lord would not ſend him to the mountain, but rather let him flee to <hi>Zoar.</hi> In which prayer holy
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38145:74"/>
                  <hi>Lot</hi> was queſtionleſs guided by the Spirit of God, to ask the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of that City, which though viſibly threatned, and in danger to be deſtroyed with the reſt, yet was in reſpect of Gods ſecret will and purpoſe, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and therefore the Lord did by his holy Spirit put it into the heart of his righteous ſervant <hi>Lot,</hi> to ask that City: In which requeſt he is preſently accepted, and the life of that City granted at his petition, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>And hee ſaid unto him: ſee, I have accepted thee concerning this thing, that I will not overthrow this City for the which thou haſt ſpoken: Haſte thee, eſcape thither, for I cannot do any thing till thou be come thither; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Name of that City was called Zoar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the infinite and admirable condeſcention of the great and holy God to the weakneſs of a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38145:74"/>poor frail man! that <hi>Lot</hi> ſhould not accept the mountain which the Lord appointed him, and yet that the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould accept <hi>Lot,</hi> and ſpare <hi>Zoar</hi> which he had ſpoken for! yet ſuch is the holy indulgence of the heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his praying children, that when through humane frailty, they cannot come up to his terms, hee out of divine pity ſtoops and comes down to theirs! and ſuch is the efficacy &amp; prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing force of Faith in prayer, that God is even overcome thereby to grant his poor praying ſervants even what they will! <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>See I have accepted thee concerning this thing, that I will not overthrow this City, for the which thou hast ſpoken:</hi> Oh well was it for <hi>Zoar</hi> that <hi>Lot</hi> ſpoke to God for it! The prayer of one juſt <hi>Lot</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers this wicked City from the common calamity and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38145:75"/>of their fellow-ſinners!</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Saints and ſervants of God have prevailed by Faith in prayer for the pulling down moſt ſpeedy vengeance, and juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon their malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ungodly enemies.</p>
               <p>Thus zealous <hi>Elijah</hi> by prayer brings down fire from Heaven upon the heads of his proud and malicious enemies (two ſeveral Captains and their fifties) who in the pride and heat of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, came to do violence to the good Prophet, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11, 12, until by theſe examples of Gods ſeverity, the reſt of that wicked party were reduced to ſome ſubmiſſion and moderation towards his faithful ſervant, who in prophecying the death of the King of <hi>Samaria,</hi> had not offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but done that which he was commanded, and allowed of God to do.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:38145:75"/>
               <p>And the ſame holy man, <hi>Elijah</hi> by prayer prevails with God to ſhut the Heavens, that it rained not for three years and ſix months, ſo that wicked <hi>Ahab, Jezabel,</hi> and the ten Tribes were for their Idolatry, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods faithful ſervants, juſtly plagued with a three years famine. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.1. compared with <hi>James</hi> 5.16, 17. <hi>The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much. Elias was a man ſubject to like paſsions as wee are, and hee prayed earneſtly that it might not rain, and it rained not on the earth by the ſpace of three years and ſix months.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus alſo the holy Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> prevails with God by Faith in prayer for the ſmiting of the King of <hi>Syria</hi>'s Army with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.18. <hi>And when they came down to him, Eliſha prayed unto the Lord, and ſaid, Smite this
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38145:76"/>people, I pray thee, with blindneſs; And hee ſmote them with blindneſs according to the Word of Eliſha.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus alſo the two faithful witneſſes under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the Lord raiſeth up to propheſie and bear witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſt 1260 daies, that is, all the time of the beaſts reign and tyranny (for ſo long hee is to continue, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.6.) have power to pull down vengeance upon their enemies, and to open and ſhut Heaven, and ſmite the earth with plagues, as oft as they will, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.5, 6. <hi>And if any man will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies. And if any man will hurt them, hee muſt in this manner bee killed. Theſe have power to ſhut Heaven, that it rain not in the daies of their prophecy, and have power over waters to turn them to blood, and to ſmite the earth with plagues,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38145:76"/>as often as they will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See here what great power the Lord hath given to his witneſs-bearing Saints and ſervants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament! whom hee raiſeth up to bear witneſs for Chriſt againſt Antichriſt, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and prophecy againſt all the abominations of the man of ſin; though they have no worldly power, nor arm of fleſh to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them, yet they are not left deſtitute, for they have power to ſhut Heaven, and to ſmite the Earth with plagues, and to call for vengeance, and the righteous judgements of God to be made manifeſt upon their enemies, for which cauſe fire is ſaid to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of their mouth; not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially, but virtually, <hi>i.e.</hi> they do by their prayers and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which proceed out of their mouth, procure vengeance from Heaven, and all the plagues and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38145:77"/>righteous judgements of God to be poured forth of the vials of his wrath upon the Antichriſtian party, who are their malicious and implacable enemies: by which means they are preſerved and protected in their witneſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing-work, all the time of their Prophecy, until the end and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing thereof; at which time by the determinate counſel of God, they are to be ſlain, and lye dead for a ſeaſon, in order to a glorious reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Saints and ſervants of God have obtained by Faith in prayer, great and wonderful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, when they have been in the greateſt danger, yea even in the very jaws of deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Great and marvellous perſonal deliverances have been obtained by Faith in prayer,
<note n="1" place="margin">Perſonal deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> or by the faithful prayers of the righteous.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:38145:77"/>
               <p>Thus that precious and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant of God, <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when hee was ſick unto the death, and had received a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory ſentence of death by the mouth of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.1. <hi>Set thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt dye, and not live:</hi> by Faith in prayer obtained the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſion of that ſentence, and was delivered in a moſt wonderful manner from the very jaws of death, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Go and ſay to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, Thus ſaith the Lord, the God of David thy Father, I have heard thy prayer, I have ſeen thy tears: behold I will add unto thy daies fifteen years.</hi> Which delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was (all circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) ſo marvellous and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, that the fame thereof ſounded as far as <hi>Babylon;</hi> the King whereof ſent his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors to congratulate the Kings recovery, and to enquire of the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38145:78"/>wonder, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.31.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo the good Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> (though an angry paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate man) when he prayed to the Lord in the fiſhes belly, and when hee was even ſwallowed up of death, without all viſible help or hope of deliverance, by Faith in prayer obtained a wonderful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance at the hands of God, who ſpake to the fiſh, and it vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited up <hi>Jonah</hi> upon the dry Land, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.10. of which prayer of his in the fiſhes belly, and the great ſalvation obtained thereby, take his own confeſſion, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.2, 5, 6, 7. <hi>And I cryed by reaſon of mine affliction unto the Lord, and hee heard mee; out of the belly of Hell cryed I, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> heardeſt my voice: The waters compaſſed mee about even to the ſoul; the depth cloſed mee round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, the weeds were wrapt about my head. I went down to the bottome
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38145:78"/>of the mountains; the earth with her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rs was about mee for ever: yet haſt thou brought up my life from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, O Lord my God. When my ſoul fainted within mee, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Lord, and my prayer came in unto thee, into thy holy Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the holy man <hi>Peter</hi> alſo being ſhut up in priſon by <hi>Herod,</hi> and bound with two chains, kept all night between two ſouldiers, the keepers alſo ſtanding before the door; being as a ſheep faſt bound and appointed for the flaughter next morning; by the prayers of the Church at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> was wonderfully delivered from death, and reſcued out of the hand of his enemies by an Angel, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Great, National,
<note n="2" place="margin">National and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</note> and publick deliverances have alſo been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at the hands of God by the faithful prayers of his people.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:38145:79"/>
               <p>Thus was <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the whole Church of God delivered from the cruel rage, great power, and proud threatnings of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> by the prayer of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (an Army of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fourſcore and five thouſand being ſlain by the Angel of the Lord in one night) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.21. <hi>Then Iſaiah the Son of Amos ſent unto Hezekiah, ſaying, Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael; whereas thou haſt prayed to mee againſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib King of Aſſyria.</hi> verſ. 33. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the King of Aſſyria; Hee ſhall not come into this City, nor ſhoot an Arrow there, nor come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it with ſhields, nor caſt a bank againſt it; by the way that hee came, by the ſame ſhall hee return, and ſhall not come into this City, ſaith the Lord: for I will defend this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſave it, for mine own ſake, and for my ſervant Davids ſake.</hi> And
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38145:79"/>
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 36. <hi>Then the Angel of the Lord went forth and ſmote in the Camp of the Aſſyrians a hundred and four ſcore and five thouſand, and when they aroſe early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, behold they were all dead corpſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the admirable and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ſtrength of Faith in prayer! that one praying faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Saint of God ſhould prevail more by one prayer of Faith, than the greateſt Conquerors in the world could ever do by force and power! a hundred and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and five thouſand ſlain by the prayers of one man! one <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> prayes, and the whole Church of God is delivered!</p>
               <p>Thus alſo when proud <hi>Haman</hi> that wicked enemy of the people of God had conſpired the utter ruine and deſtruction of the Jews, in the daies of the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; and the deſign was laid ſo
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38145:80"/>ſure (the Kings Royal aſſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained, and the decree gone forth into all the Kings Provinces, and the day ſet for the execution thereof) that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible in the eye of reaſon, that it ſhould be diſappointed, yet by the prayers of good <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the remnant of a poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed people, a moſt glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance was obtained; the Kings heart ſuddenly and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully changed; the former decree and ſentence of death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed; <hi>Mordecai</hi> highly honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and advanced, the Jews every where encouraged; wonderfully preſerved, and feared by their enemies; and wicked <hi>Haman,</hi> their proud and implacable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, with all his family deſtroyed and rooted out of the earth, <hi>Esther</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo when the children
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:38145:80"/>of <hi>Ammon, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Mount-Seir,</hi> had conſpired the utter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the people of God, and joyned together in a numerous and multitudinous Hoſt, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly invaded <hi>Judah</hi> for that end, ſuppoſing themſelves to have been ſure enough of their deſign, there being no ſtrength nor proviſion with <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> to withſtand them. A moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and glorious victory and deliverance was obtained by the prayer of good <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.3. <hi>And Jehoſaphat feared, and ſet himſelf to ſeek the Lord,</hi> v. 6. <hi>And ſaid, O Lord God of our Fathers, art not thou God in Heaven? and rulest not thou over all the Kingdomes of the Heathen? And in thine hand is there not power and might, ſo that none is able to withſtand thee? Art not thou our God, who didſt drive out the inhabitants of this Land before
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38145:81"/>thy people Iſrael, and gaveſt it to the ſeed of Abraham thy friend for ever. And they dwelt therein, and have built thee a Sanctuary therein for thy Name, ſaying, If when evil cometh upon us, as the ſword, judgement, or peſtilence, or famine, wee ſtand before this houſe, and in thy preſence (for thy Name is in this houſe) and cry unto thee in our affliction, then thou wilt hear and help. And now behold, the children of Ammon, and Moab, and Mount-Seir, whom thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not let Iſrael invade, when they came out of the Land of Egypt, but they turned from them, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them not. Behold (I ſay) how they reward us, to come to caſt us out of thy poſſeſsion, which thou haſt given us to inherit: O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might againſt this great company that cometh againſt us: neither know wee what to do, but our eyes
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38145:81"/>are upon thee. And all Judah ſtood before the Lord with their little ones, their wives and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh here is a prayer of Faith indeed! there is much of the life of Faith, and ſtrength of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this prayer of good <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſaphat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By Faith he ſees and pleads the near relation betwixt God and his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> his friend.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Faith hee preſſes God upon his Covenant and Promiſe made to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> by which hee gave the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> (which is therefore called the Land of Promiſe) to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By Faith hee acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and improveth the ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ruling power which God keepeth in his own hand over all the Kingdomes of the world,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38145:82"/>yea over the very Heathen, and thoſe that are the enemies of his Church and People; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is able at all times to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their deepeſt counſels, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint their greateſt deſigns, bridle their greateſt rage and power, ſo as to deliver his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that put their truſt in him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By Faith hee pleads the ſpecial Covenant and Promiſe of God made to <hi>Solomon</hi> on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his people at the dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Temple, and applies it to the preſent caſe in hand.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By Faith hee improves the various paſſages of providence, clearing up the innocency and integrity of his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the righteouſneſs of their cauſe, and on the contrary, declareth the guiltineſs, ingratitude, and wickedneſs of theſe ungodly nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were now combined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to ſeek the ruine of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:38145:82"/>
               <p>And upon the whole leaves the caſe with God, as a moſt righteous Judge, holy, faithful, and able to plead the caſe of his poor people in this great diſtreſs.</p>
               <p>And prevails ſo far with God by this prayer of Faith, that hee hath a gracious anſwer, and a moſt glorious return in the wonderful Salvation of the Church and People of God for whom hee prayed, and in the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction and overthrow of their potent enemies, againſt whom hee prayed: for <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Then, upon Jahaziel, &amp;c. came the Spirit of the Lord in the midſt of the Congregation. And hee ſaid, Thus ſaith the Lord unto you, be not afraid nor diſmayed by reaſon of this great multitude, for the battel is not yours, but Gods.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Yee ſhall not need to fight in this battel: ſet your ſelves, ſtand yee ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38145:83"/>with you.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>When they began to ſing and to praiſe: The Lord ſet ambuſhments againſt the children of Ammon, Moab, and Mount-Seir; which were come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Judah, and they were ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, for the children of Ammon and Moab ſtood up againſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Mount-Seir, utterly to ſlay and deſtroy them: And when they had made an end of the Inhabitants of Seir, every one helped to deſtroy another. And when Judah came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the watch tower in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they looked unto the multitude, and behold they were dead bodies fallen to the earth, and none eſcaped.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. <hi>When Jehoſaphat and his people came to take the ſpoil of them, they found among them in abundance, both riches, with the dead bodies, and precious Jewels (which they ſtript off for themſelves) more than they could carry away, and they were three daies in gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:38145:83"/>of the ſpoil, it was ſo much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh what a wonderful delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſalvation was here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by one prayer of Faith! Good <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> prayes in Faith, and prevails by prayer with God; The enemies are divided one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed one by another; <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaved with a wonderful ſalvation, and greatly enriched with the ſpoil of their enemies!</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Saints and Servants of God by Faith in prayer, have prevailed with God for the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the courſe, and changing the very law of nature in his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Creatures, ſo that they have at the command of God been ſerviceable to his Church and People, not onely beyond, but even againſt the courſe and law of nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>1</label> So holy <hi>Joſhua</hi> by Faith in prayer, commands the Sun and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:38145:84"/>Moon to ſtand ſtill, and ſtay their courſe, until hee had avenged the Lords people upon their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Then ſpake Joſhua to the Lord in the day when the Lord delivered up the Amorites before the children of Iſrael. And hee ſaid in the ſight of Iſrael, Sun, ſtand thou ſtill upon Gibeon, and thou Moon, in the valley of Ajalon.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>The Sun ſtood ſtill, and the Moon ſtayed until the people had avenged themſelves upon their enemies. Is not this written in the book of Jaſher? So the Sun ſtood ſtill in the midſt of Heaven, and haſted not to go down about a whole day!</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>There was us day like that before it, or after it, that the Lord hearkened to the voice of a man, for the Lord fought for Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the wonderful force, and prevailing efficacy of Faith i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer! that even the courſe and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38145:84"/>law of nature (which no creature can reſiſt or withſtand) ſhould thereby be ſtayed!
<note place="margin">Job 38.31, 32, 33. 34, 35 Ezek. 1.17</note> and the Sun and the Moon (which by the ordinance of God are to bee in continual motion, and move with ſuch wonderful ſpeed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6</note> as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the world in the vaſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of the Heavens in a few hours) ſhould at the word of a poor frail man, ſtand ſtill, and ſtay their courſe for the ſpace of a whole day!</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> Thus alſo holy <hi>Moſes</hi> prevails with the Lord by prayer, for the dividing the waters of the Sea, even the Red Sea, ſo that (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the law and courſe of nature) they ſtood upon an heap, and were a wall to <hi>Iſrael</hi> on the right hand, and on the left, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, Wherefore cryeſt thou unto mee? Speak unto the children of Iſrael that they go
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:38145:85"/>forward. But lift up thou thy Rod, and ſtretch out thine hand over the Sea, and divide it, and the children of Iſrael ſhall go on dry ground tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the midſt of the Sea.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>The children of Iſrael went into the midſt of the Sea upon the dry ground, and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the admirable and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous ſtrength and power of Faith in prayer! that by it the waters of the Sea, the depths of the Sea ſhould be divided, and made to ſtand upon heaps, as a wall to Gods <hi>Iſrael!</hi> and yet ſo it is; <hi>Moſes</hi> cryeth to the Lord at the Sea, even the Red Sea, and the waters are divided, and become a wall to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their paſſage towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> on the right hand, and on the left!</p>
               <p>All which (with many other bleſſed experiences of the Saints
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:38145:85"/>which might be inſtanced in) do amount to a ſufficient teſtimony and witneſs to the truth in hand; and do abundantly evince the truth of this bleſſed promiſe of the Lord Jeſus to his poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants here on earth: <hi>And all things whatſoever yee ſhall ask in prayer, beleeving, yee ſhall receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The grounds and reaſons of the point upon which this great truth is eſtabliſhed, and wherein the evidence and demonſtrations thereof do yet more fully appear, are briefly theſe three.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> The prayers of Faith, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving prayers of the Saints and ſervants of God here on earth, are heaven-born. They are influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced from Heaven by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and guidance of the holy Spirit, whoſe office it is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and manage the Saints in this great concern and work of prayer: So that the things
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38145:86"/>which they ask of God in prayer (when they ask in Faith) are not ſo much the fruit of the inward breathings, and unfeigned deſires of their own hearts and ſpirits, as of the holy and bleſſed Spirit of grace breathing in them, and teaching them to pray as they ought, which of themſelves they neither know, nor can do, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Likewiſe, the Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities: for wee know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought: But the Spirit it ſelf maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion for us with groanings which cannot be uttered: And hee that ſearcheth the heart, knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, becauſe he maketh interceſsion for the Saints, according to the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the holy Spirit of God doth not onely help and aſſiſt the Saints in the right manner of prayer, exciting their graces, quickening and drawing out their
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38145:86"/>affections, helping them to right ends and aims in prayer (all which are alſo neceſſarily required) but doth alſo ſuggeſt and teach them the very matter of their prayers; how and what to pray for, and ask of God both for themſelves and others: <hi>The Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities, for wee know not what to pray for as wee ought: But the Spirit it ſelf, &amp;c.</hi> So that the Saints are taught from Heaven what to pray for as they ought; the Spirit of God from Heaven doth teach and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them to pray here on earth according to the will of God.</p>
               <p>And how reproachfully and blaſphemouſly ſoever wicked and ungodly men do ſpeak of the (ſo called) extemporary prayers of the Saints: yet they are no leſs than heaven-born; the things which they are taught by the Spirit of God from Heaven
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38145:87"/>to ask of God in prayer. And let wicked men know, that in blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the reproaching the prayers of the Saints, they do blaſpheme the Spirit it ſelf: <hi>[But the Spirit it ſelf maketh interceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.]</hi> Wicked and ungodly men, who are ignorant of the Spirit of prayer, do exceedingly magnifie and cry up their ſtinted forms, and book-prayers, becauſe (as they imagine) compoſed and indited by holy and learned men, and that with the deepeſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and moſt ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration had of the things meet to be asked of God in prayer: And do condemn the prayers of Gods Saints, becauſe (as they judge in the darkneſs of their carnal mind, which is alwaies enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God) extemporary,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.7</note> raſh, and inconſiderate, without any deep conſideration and matter prepared before-hand: but let
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:38145:87"/>ſuch know, that the beſt of their ſtinted Forms and Book-prayers, are but indited by men on earth; and on the other hand, the prayers of Gods Saints and ſervants of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up in Faith (though extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary) are indited by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in Heaven, and given in immediately by the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Spirit, who knoweth better what is meet to be asked of God in prayer (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary) than the greateſt Biſhops, Doctors, and learned men upon earth can do, by their deepeſt conſultation.</p>
               <p>And let ſuch reſolve this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; whether are moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the will and mind of God, thoſe prayers, which are indited by the Spirit of God in Heaven, and given in from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, as all the prayers of the Saints are which they put up in Faith: or thoſe which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:38145:88"/>and impoſed by the carnal wiſdome, and coercive power of men on earth, contrary to the Word of God?</p>
               <p>And let mee adde this one word more; that the prayer of the pooreſt Saint, though en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with utmoſt humane frailties and infirmities, yet being breathed by the holy Spirit into his heart, and breathed out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in Faith by the help of the ſame Spirit, hath more of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdome, and true ſpiritual excellency in it, than the moſt magnified and admired. Form that ever was compoſed by the greateſt Doctors, and learned men in the world: For <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>That which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh: and that which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit.</hi> And again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. <hi>He that is of the earth, is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſpeaketh of the earth; hee that cometh from Heaven is above
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:38145:88"/>all.</hi> As Jeſus Chriſt came from Heaven, and therefore was above all the Prophets and Apoſtles: ſo alſo the Spirit of God cometh from Heaven, and is above all the Doctors, Biſhops, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men in the world, in teaching as how and what to pray for as wee ought.</p>
               <p>And hence it is, that true ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and heavenly prayer is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from all hypocritical ſhews, and pretences of prayer by this character, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Praying alwaies, with all prayer and ſupplication in the Spirit.</hi> True prayer and ſupplication is alwaies in the Spirit. And again, <hi>Jude</hi> 10. <hi>Praying in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumme and cloſe of the matter, is, prayers of Faith do come from God, and therefore muſt needs prevail with God; prayers of Faith are heaven-born, and therefore muſt needs finde acceptance there.</p>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:38145:89"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> The prayers of Faith, or the beleeving prayers of the Saints and People of God, do alwaies fall in with the will of God: The ſtinted Forms, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Prayers of formal Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical pretenders to Religion, do alwaies in one thing or other run counter to the will of God. In the very matter of their peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it being impoſſible that ſuch as keep themſelves to a ſtinted Form of Prayer, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige themſelves to uſe ſuch a form of words in prayer, and no others, ſhould avoid this Rock (upon which they muſt inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fall and ſplit themſelves) that the things which they ſo ask, muſt of neceſſity run croſs to the will of God: let them take what Form they will, and ſtint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the conſtant uſe of it (as the Hypocrites do) and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience will quickly teach them,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:38145:89"/>that in ſo doing they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the revealed will of God in their petitions; and therefore ſuch prayers muſt needs be very fruitleſs.</p>
               <p>But the prayers of the ſincere children of God, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed prayers of Faith, and the breathings of Gods own Spirit in them, do alwaies concur, and fall in with the will of God: And as hee that ſearcheth the heart knoweth what is the mind of the ſpirit, in the hearts of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: ſo the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.10, 11</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe hee</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the holy Spirit of God) <hi>mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth interceſsion for the Saints, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Faith looks at the will of God as her rule in asking; and in things about which the will of God is revealed, Faith will be poſitive, and ask abſolutely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:38145:90"/>an if: but in things about which the will of God is yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and unknown, Faith will ask with ſubmiſſion to the will of God. <hi>Not my will, but thy will be done,</hi> is the language of Faith in ſuch caſes: And it is as impoſſible for Faith to erre in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and to miſs of the will of God in asking, as it is for the Sun in the Firmament, to miſtake his way in his heavenly perambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: or for the waters of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to miſtake their way into the Sea, that they ſhould not come into, and coincidate with the Ocean.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever therefore the Saints do ask in Faith, they do ask according to the will of God, whether it be ſecret or revealed; For the rule which Faith looks at, is an unerring rule, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole light of Scripture-revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And the conduct and guide
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:38145:90"/>by which Faith is directed in ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is an unerring guide, even the holy Spirit of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. which perfectly knoweth and ſearcheth what is the mind and will of God in all caſes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecret or manifeſt.</p>
               <p>And it is worthy obſervation, how the poor Saints of God are oft times, by a ſecret inſtinct and conduct of the Spirit guided in prayer, to ask thoſe very things of God, which hee is about to do and bring to paſs, beyond what is revealed or made known.</p>
               <p>As when <hi>Lot</hi> asked of God in Prayer, the preſervation of the City <hi>Zoar,</hi> which was threatned, and in viſible danger of periſhing in the common deſtruction of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and yet was preſerved by the prayer of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Lot,</hi> who was queſtionleſs guided in his asking that City a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove any other,
<note place="margin">Gen. 16.19, 20, 21</note> by the ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:38145:91"/>of the Spirit, who knew what was the ſecret will and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God in that matter, and therefore taught <hi>Lot</hi> to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for it according to the will of God.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo that holy woman <hi>Hannah,</hi> when ſhee prayed for a Son, and in the pouring out of her ſpirit to the Lord in prayer, did before-hand dedicate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote him to the Lord all his daies, was queſtionleſs guided by a ſecret and ſpecial inſtinct of the ſpirit, to ask of God that very thing that was in the heart and purpoſe of God concerning her and her Son, though as yet ſecret and unknown, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.10, 11.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo the laſt Martyrs that ſuffered in the <hi>Marian</hi> daies, were taught from Heaven by the ſecret conduct of the ſpirit, to ask of God in prayer that they
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:38145:91"/>might be the laſt that ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in that manner, and that the Lord would put an end to the afflictions of his people. And were in that petition graciouſly heard and anſwered: for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the life of that wicked Queen was cut off by the hand of God: And though many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were condemned, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants iſſued out for the burning of them,
<note place="margin">Fox Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiro. vol. 3. p. 893.</note> yet the tydings of the Queens death ſtayed the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thoſe precious ſouls were, according to their petition, the laſt that ſuffered in that bloody perſecution.</p>
               <p>Whatever therefore the Saints do ask of God in prayer, by the help of his holy Spirit, and by Faith in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, they do ask according to his will, and therefore muſt needs prevail in Heaven, and have ſuch petitions granted and fulfilled on
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:38145:92"/>earth, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14, 15. <hi>And this is the confidence that wee have in him, that if wee ask any thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, hee heareth us. And if wee know that hee heareth us. Whatſoever wee ask, wee know that wee have the petitions that wee deſired of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> The prayers of the Saints of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up in Faith, do fall under the bleſſing of the mediation and interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.14.16</note> that great High Prieſt over the Houſe of God, who is entred into the Heavens, even Jeſus the Son of God, whoſe office it is to offer up the prayers of all the Saints with the ſpiritual incenſe of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, whereby they do become acceptable to God.</p>
               <p>It pertained to the office,
<note place="margin">Exod. 30.6, 7 Levit. 16.12</note> and was the cuſtome of the Prieſts under the Law to enter within the vail, and offer up the ſweet Incenſe with the prayers of the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:38145:92"/>Congregation, who uſually were without the door of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle praying at the time of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe:
<note place="margin">Luke 1.8, 9, 10</note> And the time of the Prieſts offering up Incenſe was obſerved by the Congregation as a ſpecial time and ſeaſon for prayer: And all this was to typifie and point out ſomething of the Prieſtly and Mediatorial Office of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Heb 6.19, 20. and 9.24</note> who is now entred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the vail, into the holy of holies, <hi>i. e.</hi> the heavenly places them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, there to appear in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us, as <hi>a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck:</hi> to offer up all the ſpiritual ſacrifices and ſervices of the Saints unto his Father, with the ſprinkling of his blood, and ſweet perfume and incenſe of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious merits upon them, whereby their perſons, though compaſſed with many ſins and infirmities, and their ſervices, though weak
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:38145:93"/>and imperfect in themſelves, are made infinitely acceptable and well pleaſing unto the Father through him.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">Their perſons.</note> Their perſons are made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto the Father through him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>To the praiſe of his glorious grace, wherein hee hath made us accepted in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh ye precious Saints of God, know that the acceptation of your perſons with the Father, ſtands not in your own Saintſhip, and perſonal righteouſneſs, but in the imputed righteouſneſs, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood, and merits of Jeſus Chriſt, which is made yours by Faith: So that by the blood of Jeſus ye are now made Kings and Prieſts unto his Father, and may come to the throne of grace with acceptation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.6. <hi>Unto him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood: And
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:38145:93"/>hath made us Kings and Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and his Father;</hi> therefore yee may come boldly to the throne of grace, through the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious interceſſion of Jeſus your great High Prieſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Seeing then that wee have a great High Prieſt, that is paſſed into the Heavens, Jeſus the Son of God.</hi> Verſ. 16. <hi>Let us come boldly unto the throne of grace.</hi> And again, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.12. <hi>In whom wee have boldneſs and acceſs by the Faith of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſervices,
<note n="2" place="margin">Their ſervices.</note> and ſpiritual ſacrifices of the Saints which they offer up to God in Faith, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Father through Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Yee alſo as lively ſtones are built up a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual-houſe, an holy Priesthood, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up ſpiritual ſacrifice, acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where obſerve, that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation and interceſſion of Jeſus
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:38145:94"/>Chriſt, is the procuring cauſe of all the Saints acceptation with God, both as to their perſons, and as to their ſervices, which here are called ſpiritual ſacrifice. And yee Saints of God, know, that your ſacrifices are not therefore acceptable to God, becauſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, but becauſe offered to God thorow Jeſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now it is the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Faith to lead us out of our ſelves for acceptation,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1</note> as well as for aſſiſtance, unto the blood, and righteouſneſs,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.24</note> and merits of Jeſus Chriſt, and Faith ſeeks its acceptation with the Father one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.19, 20</note> and wholly through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Jeſus the Son of God.</p>
               <p>And therefore all the prayers of the Saints, which are put up in Faith, do come under the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and glorious interceſſion of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:38145:94"/>Jeſus, and are offered up to the Father by the hand of Chriſt, who is therefore called the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Covenant, and ſaid to ſtand before the Altar, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Incenſe Altar, becauſe hee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth up continually the prayers of the Saints with his own hand, perfumed with the Incenſe of his own merits unto the Father, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3, 4. <hi>And another Angel came and stood at the Altar, having a golden Cenſer. And there was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto him much Incenſe, that he ſhould offer it with the prayers of all Saints upon the golden Altar which was before the Throne: And the ſmoke of the Incenſe which came with the prayers of the Saints, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up before God, out of the Angels hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh needs muſt the prayers of Faith, the beleeving prayers of all the Saints aſcend up before God, and prevail in Heaven,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:38145:95"/>which are offered up by the hand of this bleſſed Angel, even Jeſus, who is before the throne, And is there continually! ſo that it is alwaies the time of Incenſe with the Congregation of Gods praying people; for this bleſſed Angel is day and night before the Throne, offering up their prayers with the pure Incenſe of his merits: Jeſus the Mediator and High Prieſt of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is alway within the vail, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on this part of his Prieſtly office in Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> If the Efficacy of Faith in prayer be ſuch, that the Saints may thereby prevail in Heaven: And that all things, whatſoever they ſhall ask in prayer, beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they ſhall receive; then woe be to all ſuch as have the prayers of the Saints juſtly engaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:38145:95"/>them. It is eaſier to ſtand before the greateſt Armies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the combined powers and policies of the greateſt Monarchs and Princes in the world, than to ſtand before the prayers of two or three poor Saints, who pray in Faith, and cry day and night to God for help againſt their wicked perſecutors.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſtoried of the Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Worthies of the Old Teſtament, amongſt other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deeds, and great things which they did by Faith: That by it they put to flight the Armies of the Aliens, and ſubdued King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33. <hi>Who through Faith ſubdued Kingdomes, ſtopped the mouths of Lions, quenc hed the violence of fire, eſcaped the edge of the ſword; out of weakneſs, were made ſtrong; waxed valiant in fight; turned to flight the Armies of the Aliens.</hi> By Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> by
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:38145:96"/>prayers of Faith; for they cryed unto the Lord in their ſtraits, and under the great oppreſſions and tyranny of their enemies, they prayed to the Lord for help a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: And by Faith in prayer they obtained help from God againſt their perſecutors.</p>
               <p>Their enemies were wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully brought under, mighty Kingdomes ſubdued, and whole Armies ſtrangely conquered, and ſhamefully put to flight.</p>
               <p>Sometimes without means,
<note place="margin">Exod. 14.27, 28</note> as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſt at the Red Sea.</p>
               <p>Sometimes by weak and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible means;
<note place="margin">Judges 4.21</note> as <hi>Siſera</hi> fell by the hand of a woman. And King <hi>Herod</hi> that bloody perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<note place="margin">Act. 12.23</note> dyed by Worms or Lice. And the whole Army of the <hi>Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> with the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and all the children of the Eaſt, who lay upon the ground like Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:38145:96"/>(ſo great was their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) were put to flight by the dream of a Barley Cake tumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the Hoſt of <hi>Midian.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 5.12, 13, 14</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes by contrary means, againſt the very Law of nature, friendſhip, and natural affection. So proud and blaſphemous <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> fell by his own Sons,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 37.38</note> whilſt hee was worſhipping in the houſe of <hi>Niſeroth</hi> his God, who were wonderfully over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the power and providence of God, even againſt the Law of nature and religion, to execute the wrath of God; and avenge the cauſe of his praying-people upon this proud and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor. So alſo the children of <hi>Moab, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Mount-Seir,</hi> who were confederate againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> were by the juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God at the prayer of good <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> given up to ſuch a ſpirit of diviſion and hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:38145:97"/>themſelves,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.23, 24</note> that they fully ſet themſelves to deſtroy one another, and ceaſed not till there was not one of them left.</p>
               <p>Sometimes by preternatural and extraordinary means, where ordinary means have failed.
<note place="margin">Joſh. 10.10, 11</note> Thus the five Kings and their Armies that fought againſt <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> were ſubdued and deſtroyed chiefly by hailſtones from Heaven. And thus the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi>'s Army, conſiſting of an hundred and fourſcore and five thouſand,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 27.36</note> were ſlain in one night by the hand of an Angel. Thus the mouths of thoſe greedy and roaring Lions were ſtopped by an Angel, that they could not ſo much as touch <hi>Daniel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 1.6.22</note> And the burning deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of the fiery Furnace ſo quenched by the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Son of God, that it had no power ſo much as to ſinge the garments,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.25, 26, 27</note> or hair of the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:38145:97"/>heads of thoſe three Worthies, <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the greateſt Monarchs, Princes, Generals, Armies, and Kingdomes of the world, have not been able to ſtand before the prayers of the Saints of God, when they have prayed in Faith, and cryed to the Lord for help againſt them!</p>
               <p>Woe therefore be unto all thoſe againſt whom the Elect of God do cry for vengeance day and night! 'Tis not in the power of the greateſt worldly force and pollicy to ſecure them from the revenging hand of God: No, but ſuch muſt certainly fall before the prayers of Gods Elect, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>And ſhall not God avenge his own Elect, which cry day and night unto him; though hee bear long with them</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors) <hi>I tell you that hee will avenge them ſpeedily.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:38145:98"/>
               <p>Oh that therefore the Kings and Princes, and Rulers of the Earth would bee wiſe and take heed how by perſecuting and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the People of God, they conſtrain them to cry to Heaven againſt them: 'Tis bleſſed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which the Spirit of God gives by the mouth of his ſervant <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Pſal. 2.10. <hi>Be wiſe now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O yee Kings, be inſtructed yee Judges of the Earth: Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling. Kiſs the Son, leſt hee be angry, and yee periſh in the way: When his wrath is kindled but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>2</label> What a great mercy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing then are the Saints and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God to the Nations, and Kingdoms, and Countries where they live? who as ſo many Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or rather Kings and Prieſts, have power with God; and can
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:38145:98"/>by Faith in prayer prevail with him for any thing?</p>
               <p>What a mercy was one pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Nation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 106.23</note> when they had provoked the Lord to jealouſie by the golden Calf?</p>
               <p>What a great mercy was one praying <hi>Lot</hi> to the City <hi>Zoar?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.21</note> which ſhould have been deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> had not <hi>Lot</hi> prayed for it?</p>
               <p>What a great bleſſing was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Jacob</hi> (who was a great wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with God in prayer,
<note place="margin">Gen. 32.24.28</note> and as a Prince, had power with God, and prevailed, and upon that account had his name changed from <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> to <hi>Iſrael</hi>) what a mercy I ſay was hee to the whole Family of his Unckle <hi>Laban,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 30.27</note> whilſt he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed there?</p>
               <p>That ſpeech of the Lord to King <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and his People, concerning <hi>Abraham</hi> a poor tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:38145:99"/>and ſtranger, who came but to ſojourn in his Country for a time, is very remarkable, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Now therefore restore the man his Wife; for hee is a Prophet, and hee ſhall pray for thee, and thou ſhalt live.</hi> Wrath was gone out from the Lord againſt King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi> and his People. And the prayers of <hi>Abraham,</hi> a poor ſtranger, prevail in Heaven for the life of <hi>Abimelech,</hi> who otherwaies was but a dead man, and for thoſe in his houſe, whoſe wombs were faſt cloſed up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of <hi>Sarah Abraham</hi>'s Wife,
<note place="margin">Gen. 20.3.17, 18</note> whom <hi>Abimelech</hi> had ſinfully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to him. Their own ſin (not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſojourning) had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured wrath againſt them. And <hi>Abraham</hi> by prayer procureth ſparing and healing mercy for them! A ſinning Court, who daily provoke the Lord againſt themſelves and ſubjects,
<note place="margin">☞</note> had
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:38145:99"/>need of ſome praying ſouls daily to intercede for them!</p>
               <p>How great therefore is the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the wicked, who look upon the People of God as the onely troublers of their <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 18.17</note> and attribute the cauſe of all their calamities and troubles to the Lords faithful ſervants; which they procure unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their own wickedneſs? Juſtly therefore may the Lords People anſwer ſuch <hi>Ahabs,</hi> in the words of that old non-conformiſt and good Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Wee have not troubled Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, but thou, and thy Fathers houſe, in that yee have forſaken the Commandements of the Lord, and thou haſt followed Baalim!</hi> 'Tis not the zealous and conſcientious non conformiſt, that troubles the Court and Country, but the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous and ſuperſtitious par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who caſt off the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:38145:100"/>of the Lord, and ſet up their own inventions,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.29 Rev. 13.12, 15, 16</note> and as a greater aggravation of their wickedneſs, would compel others to ſin with them.</p>
               <p>Oh that therefore the eyes of the Nations, of the Kings and Judges of the earth were opened to diſcern aright, and to ſee who are the troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and who are the chariots and horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof: Well! that bleſſed day is a coming, wherein the Kings of the earth even ſhall hate that ſcarlet whore,
<note place="margin">Rev. 17.16, 17</note> &amp; tear her fleſh, &amp; burn her with fire, even ſo <hi>Amen.</hi> The good Lord haſten it in his due time, and let all the Saints ſay, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi> Well then! whatever wicked men ſay, whatever proud men ſay out of the blindneſs, and hardneſs, and unbeleef of their hearts; yet the zealous and conſcientious non-conformiſts are not the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:38145:100"/>troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 2.12 Rev. 16.13, 14</note> but the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and Horſe-men thereof: Are not the Kings enemies but his and their Countries beſt friends?
<note place="margin">Rev. 19.19, 20, 21</note> and wicked men will be found at laſt to be the worſt ſubjects and enemies both to their King and Country.</p>
               <p>Let the Nations, Kings and Princes of the earth therefore know, that 'tis their beſt intereſt to cheriſh, protect and incourage a praying and a holy people, though they cannot in all things conform to their laws and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms in the matters of Gods moſt holy worſhip, about which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is ſo jealous,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5 Dan. 3.17, 18. &amp; 6.10</note> and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo truly and tenderly conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious. And the prayers of ſuch a people ſhall prevail more in Heaven for their King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in order to their defence and ſafety, than all the Chariots and Horſe-men, Souldiers &amp; Armies,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:38145:101"/>Power and Policy that the whole world can afford them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>3</label> Then O ye Saints and Servants of the moſt high God, who have received the ſpirit of Adoption, and have an intereſt in Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great High Prieſt, who is entred into the Heavens for us, even Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Son of God, come boldly and daily to the throne of grace, improve your intereſt in Heaven, and try what faith and prayer will do there for the help of your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, your poor afflicted brethren abroad in the world, for the conſolation and deliverance of <hi>Zion,</hi> that City of God, and for the confuſion and deſtruction of mighty <hi>Babel,</hi> that Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the earth, who hath corrupted the whole earth with her fornications, involved the whole Creation in ſuch a woful bondage and thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and made her ſelf drunk
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:38145:101"/>with the blood of Saints and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus.
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16</note> Come boldly I ſay to the throne of Grace,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.7</note> and cry mightily to Heaven even day and night,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 62.6, 7</note> and give the Lord no reſt till he doth ariſe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 87.3</note> and make his <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth, and fulfil all thoſe glorious things which are ſpoken of that City of God, and execute all the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments written againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>binde her Kings in chains,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 149.7, 8, 9</note> and her Nobles in links of Iron.</hi> This ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour have all his Saints.</p>
               <p>O ye Saints, this is an honour that the God of Heaven and earth hath put upon you (by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the anointing and unction of the holy one that is upon you) for that end to be the witneſſes of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rev. 11.3, 4, 5, 6</note> and to open and ſhut Heaven by your prayers, and to ſmite the earth with plagues as often as ye will, to pray down the mighty Kingdome of <hi>Babel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 11.15</note>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:38145:102"/>which is Antichriſt, and to pray up the glorious and everlaſting Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt;
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.22, 13</note> to pray out theſe old Heavens, and old earth, wherein dwelleth wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and to pray in the new Heavens, and new Earth, wherein ſhall dwel righteouſneſs &amp; peace.</p>
               <p>This is an honour, I ſay, which the God of Heaven and Earth hath put upon you, that ye ſhould ſtand before the God of the whole earth,
<note place="margin">Zech. 4.14</note> and be inſtrumental and influential in and about theſe great things.</p>
               <p>And this honour can no man take from you; this is a priviledge and honour given you from Heaven, and 'tis not in the power of all the devils in hell by tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor all the powers of earth by perſecuting, to take it from you; they may caſt you into priſons, lay you in the darkeſt dungeons, drive you into exile and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:38145:102"/>but ſtill where-ever you are, what-ever your outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be; Heaven is open over your heads, and the ſpirit of grace is nigh your hearts, ye may have acceſs to the throne of grace, they cannot keep out the Spirit from you, nor ſhut out your prayers from aſcending before God; if they will not ſuffer you to utter words,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.13, 15 Rom. 8.26, 27</note> ye may pour out your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and ſigh and groan inwardly, and hee who ſearcheth the heart, knoweth what is the mind of the ſpirit. I ſay, ye may come freely and boldly to the throne of grace, the way is open, and none can ſhut it; 'tis a new and a living way, not of works, but of grace; not by the blood of Bulls and of Goats, but by the blood of Jeſus; neither your ſins, nor your enemies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can ſhut it; if it were an old Covenant way of acceſs by works, and mans righteouſneſs,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:38145:103"/>your ſins might ſhut it, and you not be able to enter into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt; or if it were a way of acceſs by carnal and external ſacrifices, your enemies might ſhut it, and make the daily ſacrifice to ceaſe,
<note place="margin">Dan. 8.11.</note> either by denying you liberty, or wherewithall to ſacrifice.</p>
               <p>But now ſeeing it is a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant way of acceſs, not by works, and mans righteouſneſs, but by free grace, and Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs imputed by Faith to them that beleeve not by exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſacrifice, but by the blood and ſpirit of Jeſus the Son of God; lift up your heads, and know that 'tis not in the power of your ſins, or enemies, to hinder your daily acceſs to the throne of grace; if you have Faith but as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, and come in the exerciſe of that Faith by the blood of Jeſus, yee may ask and have, prevail with God by
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:38145:103"/>prayer for all things whatſoever; there is nothing too great, or too good for God to beſtow upon you; he hath ſet you no bounds, but bids you ask what you will: <hi>And all things, whatſoever ye ſhall ask in prayer, beleeving, ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</hi> Let mee therefore cloſe up this exhortation with the words of the holy Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>Having therefore bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to enter into the holieſt by the blood of Jeſus, by a new and living way, which he hath conſecrated for us, through the vail, that is to ſay, his fleſh; and having an high Prieſt over the houſe of God: Let us draw near with a true heart, and in full aſſurance of Faith: having our hearts ſprinkled from an evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>laſt.</label> Laſtly, And to ſhut up all, O ye <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who as Princes have power with him thus to prevail in Heaven, that all things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:38145:104"/>ye ask in prayer, beleeving, ye are ſure to receive; give all the glory unto Jeſus Chriſt, and caſt your crowns down at his feet, and give glory to the Lamb, through whom alone it is that ye thus overcome and prevail by Faith againſt all the powers of Hell and Earth.</p>
               <p>Oh learn that new ſong, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Thou art worthy to take the book, and to open the ſeals thereof</hi> (not we are worthy, but thou art worthy) to have honour, and glory, and bleſſing, and power: As <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13. for <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood, out of every kindred, tongue, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and nation, and haſt made us unto our God Kings and Prieſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh know, and freely confeſs before Angels and men, that it is not by your own holineſs, or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, that ye do any of theſe great things, but by Faith in the
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:38145:104"/>name, the bleſſed and holy name of Jeſus; let the ſame mind be in you, that was in the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who when they had done a great work upon the impotent man (who was lame from his Mothers womb, which drew the eye of the people with great admiration towards them) did humble and abaſe themſelves, that Chriſt alone might be magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, &amp; have all the glory of what they had done, directing the eye, and expectation of the people from them unto Jeſus the Son of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Ye men of Iſrael, why marvel yee at this? Or why look yee ſo earneſtly on us? as though by our own power or holineſs we had made this man to walk? The God of Abraham, Iſaac, and of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, the God of our Fathers hath glorified his Son Jeſus, whom ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>His name, through Faith in his name
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:38145:105"/>hath made this man ſtrong, whom ye ſee and know. Yea the Faith which is by him, hath given him this perfect ſoundneſs in the preſence of you all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh here is a choice and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirit indeed! here is the life and glory of Faith indeed! to do great things in the name and ſtrength of Chriſt; &amp; then to give all the glory back again to him!</p>
               <p>Oh ye Saints and Servants of God, know, that 'tis not by your own power and holineſs, by your own Saintſhip and worthineſs, but by the power and holineſs, by the blood and righteouſneſs, by the mediation and interceſſion of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that ye do any of theſe great things by Faith in prayer.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſay again and again, give all the glory to Jeſus Chriſt; let nothing be given to faith, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be given to prayer; nothing be given or aſcribed to your own Saintſhip or holineſs, but let all
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:38145:105"/>the glory be given to God and to the Lamb who is in the midſt of the throne, but the holy Angels, the four beaſts, &amp; four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Elders, with all the heavenly hoſt, whoſe number is ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ten thouſand, are all about the throne, not ſharing the glory &amp; honor with Jeſus Chriſt, though they have been miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially inſtrumental in the hand of Chriſt to accompliſh theſe great works; but giving all the glory to him, and to him alone, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.11.12, 13, 14. <hi>And I beheld, and I heard the voyce of many Angels round about the throne, and the beaſts and the Elders, and the number of them was ten thouſand times ten-thouſand, and thouſand of thouſands. Saying with a loud voyce, worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain, to receive power and riches and wiſdome, and ſtrength, and honor, and glory, and bleſſing. And every creature which
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:38145:106"/>is in Heaven, and on earth, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth, and ſuch as are in the ſea, and all that are in them, heard I ſaying, bleſſing, honor, glory, and power be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever and ever. And the four Beaſts, and the four and twenty Elders fell down and worſhipped him that liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever and ever. Even ſo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let all the Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and all the Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and all creatures, perſons, and things be nothing, be leſſe then nothing, be overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed and diſ-appear, that Jeſus Chriſt the Lamb of God may be all in all, and appear in his glory, and ſhine as the Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the higheſt heavens for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>And let all the Saints and holy Angels, who are but ſtars, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and know, that they ſhine but
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:38145:106"/>with a borrowed light, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt diſappear at the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this glorious Sun, that all the world may behold his face in Righteouſneſs, and the whole earth be enlightned with his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let him be true, and every man a Lyer, let him be holy, and every man a ſinner; he muſt increaſe, but we must decreaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let every Saint and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God ſay, let every friend of the Bridegroom ſay, <hi>This my joy therefore is fulfilled:</hi> for this is the great end of the Saints, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs unto, &amp; acceptance with the Father through Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.13. <hi>And whatſoever ye ſhal aske in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son.</hi> If God and Jeſus Chriſt be hereby glorified, we have our end, our all.</p>
               <p>The ſumm, and ſcope, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:38145:107"/>of all our faith, and hope of all our praying, preaching, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reading, doing, and ſuffering, is this,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 61.3.</note> 
                  <hi>That he may be glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this therefore let us joy and rejoyce, in this let our ſouls ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſſe, and take up, as in our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual center and Heavenly reſt? as in our <hi>Canaan,</hi> our Heaven, our all, which is dearer and ſweeter to us then our reputations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, liberties, lives, yea then our very ſouls, then all our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments. That Jeſus Chriſt, and the Father in him is glorified and exalted by the great things that he doth and will do in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for his poor, ſinful, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, tempted, and afflicted Servants here on earth. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 8. <hi>Conſidering the end of their converſation Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:38145:107"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle, page 2. line 6. for form read from, and page 4. line 11. read thoſe. In the Book, p. 59. l. 12. r. life, p. 75 l. 22. blot out the, p. 83. l. 2. r. Non-Ordinancers, p. 153, l. 13. r. Demonſtration.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
